<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians daily sacrifice duly offer'd, or, A practical discourse teaching the right performance of prayer by Lancelot Addison.</title>
            <author>Addison, Lancelot, 1632-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26359</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25228</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08801152</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08801152</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41876</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26359)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41876)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1273:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians daily sacrifice duly offer'd, or, A practical discourse teaching the right performance of prayer by Lancelot Addison.</title>
                  <author>Addison, Lancelot, 1632-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 143 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer.</term>
               <term>Devotional exercises.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41876:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41876:1"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIANS Daily Sacrifice, Duly Offer'd. OR A Practical Diſcourſe Teaching the Right Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of <hi>Prayer.</hi> By LANCELOT ADDISON, D. D. Dean of <hi>Lichfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>S. James IV. 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Ye ask and receive not, becauſe ye ask amiſs.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> at the Weſt end of S. <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41876:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41876:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable Sir BENJAMIN BATHURST.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN ſetting ſo Eminent a Name before ſo mean a Work, ſhews that I have as little skill in <hi>Dedication,</hi> as they have in <hi>Architecture,</hi> who erect a <hi>Stately En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance</hi> to a Houſe of no Competent Reception. To which Indecorum I was carried by a <hi>Zeal</hi> I have ever had to own to the <hi>World</hi> the Honour and Advantage that for many, many Years I have receiv'd from Your ſteady Friendſhip. Which was begun in a Foreign <hi>Nation,</hi> where You added no ſmall Credit and Reputation to Your <hi>Own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I therefore Addreſs You, <hi>(SIR)</hi> as a Friend, the Nobleſt Title upon Earth, and come not meerly to crave Your Patronage, but to pay You a Debt. A Debt of Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, which as it will alway be Due, ſo it ſhall alway be Paid.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41876:3"/>
            <p>But I know Time, and Buſineſs, is precious to You, and therefore I will not farther treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs upon either, than to beg Your Pious Acceptance of this <hi>Small Treatiſe,</hi> and that You would look upon it as a Pledge of my <hi>Grateful Senſe</hi> of Your Favours, and of the great Zeal I have for Your Eternal <hi>Welfare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, <hi>SIR,</hi> being no Friend to the Common matter of <hi>Letters Dedicatory,</hi> pardon me that inſtead of enlarging upon Your <hi>Merits</hi> I apply my ſelf to <hi>Prayer</hi> (the Subject of the enſuing Diſcourſe) That You, and Your Lady, and Children, may long, long Enjoy <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>Proſperity;</hi> and that the God of Bleſſings may Bleſs You with all Divine Graces on Earth, and in Heaven Crown You with Glory.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Lichfield,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>July 8. 1698.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Obliged, and Humble Servant</hi> L. Addiſon</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:41876:3"/>
            <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>TWO very different Opinions, and both ſufficiently erroneous, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Holy Exerciſe of Prayer, got very early footing among the Juda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>izing Chriſtians, (to whom St. <hi>James,</hi> the pious Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> wrote his cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Epiſtle.) Some there were among them in whoſe eſteem Prayer was ſunk ſo low, that they thought it either wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary, or at moſt but a thing of <hi>Choice</hi> and not <hi>Duty,</hi> and of that Indifference that they might uſe or let it alone as they pleas'd, without any Offence to God, or hindrance to themſelves. And of this Opinion were thoſe <hi>who coveted and had not, who kill'd, and deſired to have, and could not obtain;</hi> Who Fought and Warr'd, <hi>yet they had not, becauſe they asked not.</hi> S. <hi>James 4.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All their Coveting, Envying, Contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Fighting, brought them in no
<pb facs="tcp:41876:4"/>advantage, becauſe they neglected <hi>Prayer,</hi> the only means of rendring their <hi>honeſt Endeavours</hi> Proſperous and Succeſsful.</p>
            <p>And as theſe were apt to neglect and ſet too ſmall an Eſteem upon <hi>Prayer,</hi> ſo there were others who had a notion of <hi>Prayer</hi> as much bending to the other Extreme. For they laid ſo much ſtreſs upon it, and thought it ſo efficacious, as to expect that every thing muſt of courſe be granted them, if they ſought for it in <hi>Prayer.</hi> The <hi>former</hi> made <hi>Prayer</hi> in a manner uſeleſs as to the obtaining of any thing; the <hi>latter</hi> thought it able to obtain all things. Being of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the meer Exerciſe thereof had ſuch a power with God, as to prevail with him even for ſuch things as they deſign'd to <hi>conſume upon their Luſts,</hi> and to ſupport their Envy, Malice, Covetouſneſs and Ambition.</p>
            <p>How far the Preſent Age (guilty of all ſorts of vile Opinions and Practices) is gone in this diſtemper, I leave every one to make his own obſervations; my purpoſe being to return at leaſt an Honeſt, if not a Satisfactory anſwer to the Requeſt made to me, namely, <hi>To give a familiar account
<pb facs="tcp:41876:4"/>of the Holy Duty of Prayer.</hi> So that without further <hi>Preface</hi> I ſhall begin with the true Notion thereof, as that which will more eaſily lead to the knowledge of its <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> and Importance.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:41876:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41876:5"/>
            <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the true Notion of Prayer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NOT to ſpend time about the Grammatical meaning of the Words by which <hi>Prayer</hi> in all <hi>Languages</hi> is ſignified, I ſhall briefly ſet down what <hi>Prayer</hi> is, and what it does imply.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Prayer,</hi> according to S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> (in Pſal. 85.) is, <hi>A ſpeaking</hi> to <hi>God; When you read the Scripture,</hi> ſaith the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>God ſpeaks to you, but when you Pray, you ſpeak to him.</hi> From which words <hi>Drexelius</hi> took occaſion to define <hi>Prayer, The Converſation and Diſcourſe of the ſoul with God.</hi> Which is agreeable to the Notion of this Duty in <hi>Job</hi> 15.4. for (as <hi>Druſius</hi> obſerves) the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Word there uſed for <hi>Prayer,</hi> ſignifies to have a <hi>Familiar Converſe</hi> with the Almighty. And the <hi>Greek</hi> Fathers ſpeak of it in the ſame ſenſe, when they call it <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>familiar talking with,</hi> or,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41876:6"/>
               <hi>unto God.</hi> For in it you unboſom your ſelf, and open your heart and mind unto <hi>him,</hi> as a man would do unto his <hi>Friend</hi> in whom he moſt confides.</p>
            <p>Some of the Antients, ſpeaking <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torically</hi> of <hi>Prayer,</hi> call it a <hi>Chain of gold hanging down from heaven to draw men up thither, and to bring them into the more immediate preſence of God, and to an intimate acceſs to the Fountain of all Goodneſs.</hi> And it is ſuppos'd to make ſuch a Change in us, as if it plac'd us on <hi>Mount Tabor,</hi> to enjoy a kind of Transfiguration of the Soul; which by the means of <hi>Prayer,</hi> as in a Glaſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds the glory of the Lord, and is changed into the ſame Image from glory to glory.</p>
            <p>The eye of the Soul by the help of <hi>Prayer</hi> (as truly as the eye of the Body feeds it ſelf with the beauty of the fields) does refreſh and recreate it ſelf with the <hi>Excellencies</hi> of God, and the Perfections of the Holy <hi>Jeſus.</hi> From whom it receives whatever it can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and through whom it avoids what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it has cauſe to fear. <hi>In Prayer</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41876:6"/>(ſaith <hi>Albertus Magnus) the ſoul is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the ſource and ſpring of all help and comfort, bounty and goodneſs It brings a man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to know God, and knowing to love him; and loving, to ſeek him; and in ſeeking to take pains;</hi> and in taking pains, to find him.</p>
            <p>But theſe and the like ſayings of the Antients, concerning <hi>Prayer,</hi> ſerve rather to expreſs the Worth and the Effects of it, than to declare its Nature any farther than that from ſuch like expreſſions we may reaſonably infer that, <hi>Prayer implies a great deal more than</hi> telling over a few <hi>Beads</hi> (as is the way of ſome) or, the bare reciting ſo many words or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences form'd and compos'd into that which we call a <hi>Prayer</hi> (which is to be fear'd is the caſe of many.) A man may ſay a thouſand of theſe, and that too with great outward ſeriouſneſs and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure, and yet be far from that which is truly and properly to be called <hi>Praying.</hi> For nothing deſervedly bears that name wherein there is not an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the ſoul, and a lifting up of the heart to God, as to the Original
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41876:7"/>of our <hi>being;</hi> with a fervent deſire to be made like unto him. So that you cannot be truly ſaid to <hi>pray,</hi> unleſs the Soul ſo far gets looſe from the entangle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the world and the body, as not only to look up to the place from whence it came, but to make ſome ſort of approaches towards it, and to him who dwelleth there, and who is the Author of its <hi>being,</hi> and the proper Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of its <hi>love.</hi> There muſt be an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt endeavour to be united to God, to become one with him, to partake of his Divine nature, or at leaſt to bear as much of his image and likeneſs, with reſpect to holineſs and purity, as we can. In the Act of <hi>Praying</hi> (if we do it as we ought) we make an oblation of our ſouls and bodies to the <hi>Eternal Being,</hi> and declare our dependence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his infinite Goodneſs, and an entire ſubjection to his <hi>Infinite Power.</hi> We ſo place our ſelves to advantage before the throne of his <hi>Divine Majeſty,</hi> as to have the dimneſs of our Underſtandings en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten'd by the brightneſs of <hi>heavenly light,</hi> and our minds (cold and dead
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41876:7"/>as they are) made warm and enliven'd by the beams of the <hi>Everlaſting Sun.</hi> Our actions in the mean time are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be ſo influenc'd as for the future to be conform'd to the excellent model and pattern ſet us by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, ſo as to become fit objects of Divine Love and Compaſſion. It is to him, <hi>to the Holy Jeſus,</hi> and to the treading in his foot-ſteps, we are ſo cloſely to apply our ſelves, as that it may beget in us a ſtrong deſire to be joyn'd unto him, and to be one with him, not enduring the thoughts of ever being ſeparated from him. This is what either <hi>Prayer</hi> ſhould produce in every pious ſoul, or what we ought to wiſh it might, and which it will, when it is in its due perfection, and when we have been ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd in its practice.</p>
            <p>It's true, ſuch flights and raptures, ſuch fervours and tranſports, (as ſome may be ſuppos'd to have in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion) ſuch a near intercourſe with God, as <hi>prayer</hi> in its perfection implies, ought not to be look'd upon as the only ſign of praying as we ought, or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41876:8"/>praying to any purpoſe. The want of this indeed is to be imputed to the weight of thoſe Corruptions wherewith the ſoul is clogg'd and preſs'd down, and kept from being elevated to the contemplation of the tranſcendent <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and adorable <hi>excellencies</hi> of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature. But then a great deal of this (ſo long as we continue cloth'd with Fleſh) is what we cannot help. And ſeeing <hi>wandring</hi> of <hi>thoughts, coolneſs</hi> of <hi>affection, want of attention,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times no ſmall defects <hi>in outward beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> (arguing too much inward ſloth and negligence) may in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure be owing to <hi>Infirmity,</hi> or <hi>Inad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertency,</hi> God will no doubt accept of our <hi>ſincere endeavour</hi> and <hi>deſire</hi> that the ſoul ſhould keep upon the wing, and do its part in all reſpects whilſt we are upon our knees, our hands lift up to heaven, and our mouths uttering our Petitions in the moſt decent Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions we can think of, and with profound humility and reſignation to the will of God to grant what he thinks fit: ſhewing all the dependence
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41876:8"/>upon his goodneſs and favour that we are able to expreſs. If there be thus much obſerv'd by us toward <hi>praying as we ought,</hi> we need not deſpair of being heard for want of more, that is, for want of <hi>praying</hi> like a Saint, or feeling in our ſelves the Holy Ardours which are peculiar to ſome men. But ſtill a ſincere <hi>deſire</hi> and <hi>endeavour</hi> to come up to the height and perfection of this Heavenly exerciſe, is no more than what is <hi>of</hi> the very eſſence of <hi>Prayer,</hi> and without which we cannot promiſe to our ſelves any great benefit from our performance of it.</p>
            <p>And thus much being ſaid in general of the nature of <hi>Prayer</hi> (whereof more may be met with in the ſequel of this Diſcourſe) it may not be amiſs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the Duty by acquainting you with the neceſſity of <hi>Prayer;</hi> and to ſhew that it is what God has at all times ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and which has accordingly been paid him in all Ages of the World, and the conſequence has ſhown God's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41876:9"/>
            <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the Neceſſity of</hi> Prayer <hi>in General.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN matters of Religion things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come neceſſary to be done, either as they are enjoyn'd by God in the way of <hi>Service</hi> due to him; or, as a <hi>means</hi> of bringing ſome conſiderable advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to his Creatures. Now, <hi>Prayer</hi> is neceſſary in both reſpects. And firſt as a <hi>Duty</hi> in the way of <hi>Service</hi> to be paid to God, which needs no other proof but this, <hi>That it is an eminent part of his Worſhip.</hi> Now <hi>Worſhip</hi> is that by which in an eſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we acknowledge the <hi>God-head,</hi> and therefore is to be look'd upon as that which is indiſpenſibly requir'd at our hands.</p>
            <p>In the Sacred Hiſtory of the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diluvian World we read, <hi>That men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to call upon the Name of the Lord,</hi> Gen. 4.26. which words (tho' they will bear another interpretation) do
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41876:9"/>according to the moſt natural conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of them, demonſtrate, <hi>That Prayer is an Act of homage which from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was paid unto the Almighty.</hi> 'Tis true we find no <hi>poſitive Law</hi> for doing this: there was not then (as there is now) any command enjoyning or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring men to <hi>Pray.</hi> Nor indeed was there need of any. For the <hi>Common light</hi> of Nature ſufficiently directed all men to this performance. And as we find no <hi>Nation</hi> was ever ſo barbarous as to deny the exiſtence of a God, ſo none was ever heard of who did not own themſelves obliged to <hi>Pray</hi> to that which they acknowledg'd for their God.</p>
            <p>In the firſt age of the World, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was mightily ſuppreſs'd by wicked men, till the time of <hi>Enoſh,</hi> but then God was pleas'd to move the hearts of the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>pious</hi> to reſtore Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and to <hi>call</hi> upon his <hi>Name.</hi> And afterwards when the <hi>Heathen World</hi> fell into wild and extravagant opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions about the God-head, aſcribing it to ſuch things as were wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41876:10"/>of the excellencies, which were ſuppos'd to go along with it, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying therein a great infatuation and ſtupidity;) yet they ſtill invok'd what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they call'd their <hi>Deity.</hi> And tho' nothing could be more ſenſeleſs and abſurd than to fancy that to be a <hi>God</hi> which they could <hi>make</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy</hi> at their pleaſure; tho' it was a deep degree of <hi>infatuation</hi> to pray to a <hi>Snake</hi> or <hi>Crocodile</hi> for <hi>protection</hi> (which were ready every hour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour them:) and tho' it was a moſt ſottiſh, unmanly conceit to beg health of a <hi>Fever,</hi> and to ſeek for recovery at the <hi>Altar</hi> of the <hi>Plague</hi> (which things ſound ſo odd that one would not imagine ſuch Deities could ever have been thought of) and tho' (I ſay) nothing could be more unreaſonable and unmanly than to worſhip ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Beings, nor more contradictory to the Nature of God, yet amidſt theſe abſurdities (apparent in the Idolatry of the Gentiles) and erroneous <hi>choice</hi> of their God, they were ſtill truly Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox in concluding it was their duty
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41876:10"/>to worſhip whatever they eſteem'd to be ſo. They were perſwaded there was in <hi>that</hi> to which they aſcrib'd Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity all the Attributes that render'd it fit for their <hi>Adoration:</hi> namely, ſuch as Power, Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and All-ſufficiency. For they muſt needs think it unreaſonable to ſeek to that for help, which could not be ſuppos'd was able to give it. And this they knew muſt be the caſe of every thing that was deſtitute of <hi>Power, Wiſdom,</hi> &amp;c. And tho' the gods of the Heathens were of this ſort, yet whilſt they believed them to be Gods, they believ'd alſo that they were bound to worſhip them. Of which Worſhip Prayer or Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation was ever thought ſo eminent a branch, that it was wont to be put for the whole ſyſtem of <hi>Divine Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the <hi>Common light</hi> of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould not clearly enough diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, That Prayer is a chief and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal part of that worſhip and homage, which is indiſpenſibly due to the All-wiſe Creator of the World, yet the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41876:11"/>
               <hi>Scriptures</hi> make it undoubtably evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. And the many Texts wherein God promiſes to hear your Prayers plainly imply a Command to make them. <hi>Call upon me,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and I will anſwer thee.</hi> Jer. 33.3. <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall call upon the name of the Lord, ſhall be deliver'd,</hi> Joel 3.32. <hi>Whatſoever ye ſhall ask the Father in my name,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>he ſhall give it you: ask and ye ſhall receive, that your joy may be full.</hi> S. John 16.23, 24. <hi>Ask and it ſhall be given you, ſeek and ye ſhall find, knock and it ſhall be open'd unto you. For every one that asketh, receiveth, and he that ſeeks, finds, and to him that knocks it ſhall be opened.</hi> S. Matth. 7.7, 8, 9. In all which and the like paſſages of Holy Writ, there is imply'd both a command to pray, and promiſe to be heard. Pſal. 65.2. <hi>Thou that heareſt the prayer unto thee</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>ſhall all fleſh come:</hi> meaning. <q rend="inline">That every man ought to betake himſelf to God's ſervice, and that none who has any care of Piety or ſenſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, will be negligent and remiſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41876:11"/>in imploring the divine goodneſs, and making his requeſts known unto God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If you ſeriouſly conſider God's dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings with men, you will ſee that they are made up of abundant Mercy, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and Bounty. All which you devoutly acknowledge and praiſe, when you rightly addreſs him with your Prayers. And by if a ſteady obedience you keep faſt to his Law, patiently waiting his good time and pleaſure, perſevering in ſincere applications to him, relying ſolely upon him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſorting to any other, or uſing any Indirect means for your ſupport; he then will ſeaſonably grant your pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, ſuccour you in your greateſt neceſſities, and deliver you in the moſt imminent dangers. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.17, 18, 19. <hi>For the Lord is nigh unto all that call upon him faithfully. He will fulfil the deſire of them that fear him, he will hear their cry, and will ſave them. He is righteous in all his ways, and holy in all his works.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:41876:12"/>
            <p>Holineſs and Veracity are his two great inſeparable Attributes. His Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is viſible in all his actions and works of Providence: in which he is ſo far from being the leaſt occaſion of men's ſinning, that he does all that can be done to rational and free Agents to keep them from it. He enlightens their minds, and ſanctifies their hearts, intending by this means either to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their innocence, or, as far as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to reſtore it, after they have loſt it. But if you, or any one, be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy as not to be wrought upon by this method, then he lets ſuch know that he means to puniſh them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their works.</p>
            <p>And next as to God's Veracity, this is apparent in all his words; for he never affirms what is not moſt true, nor promiſes what he does not fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to perform. And therefore ſeeing he has ſaid, <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Call upon me, and I will anſwer thee,</hi> and, <hi>Ask, and ye ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</hi>
               </q> Since he is <hi>nigh to all that call upon him;</hi> that is, willing and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to grant their requeſts, he will not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41876:12"/>fail of his word. And tho you find your ſelf wavering, light and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and apt to be turn'd with every blaſt, diverted by every allurement, and to deal with your beſt and chiefeſt vows, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> with his new cords which he broke at the naming of a <hi>Philiſtin;</hi> yet with God there is no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs, <hi>He is the Lord, and changeth not; he is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever:</hi> whatſoever then he has ſaid ſhall certainly come to paſs. For <hi>he is righteous in all his ways,</hi> and never fails of making good his Title of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Hearer of Prayers. When <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becka</hi> was childleſs, <hi>Iſaac</hi> entreated the Lord for her, and ſhe conceiv'd. <hi>Moſes</hi> beſought the Lord to remove the Plague he had brought upon <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> and his Prayer was granted. <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> labouring under the reproach of barrenneſs, pour'd out her ſoul unto God, and he gave her a ſon. <hi>Ezra</hi> and his Country-men, pray'd that God would ſafely guard them home out of their <hi>Babylonian</hi> bondage, and he was intreated by them, and his hand was
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41876:13"/>upon them for good. When the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> in the firſt battle with the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtins</hi> were defeated, their Judges ſlain, and the Ark of God taken Priſoner; yet <hi>Samuel</hi> cry'd to the Lord to give them better ſucceſs, the Lord heard him, and fought from heaven in their behalf; diſcomfiting the enemy with thunder and lightning. And when ever the <hi>Jews</hi> were in affliction, they no ſooner made their unfeign'd ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications unto God, but he ſent them relief, he deliver'd them from their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors; and by his all-wiſe and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Providence</hi> directed them to ſome auſpicious, ſucceſsful means of redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their grievances, and either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored them to their former conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or gave them one that was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>I mention theſe Examples of God's granting the Prayers of his Servants, with no other intent but to confirm your aſſurance of his never failing to fulfil his promiſe of hearing thoſe who duly call upon him. And he ſeems ſo ready to do this, that he will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41876:13"/>work miracles, than faithful prayers ſhall return empty: as it hapned in the caſe of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> at whoſe requeſt God made the Sun <hi>ſtand ſtill upon Gibeon, and the moon in the valley of Ajalon,</hi> Joſh. 10.12. And when many have been brought to the loweſt ebb of miſery and want, even then has God been rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at hand to hear the groanings of the Priſoners, and to looſe <hi>thoſe who were appointed to die,</hi> Pſal. 86. ſignally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing his power and providence in ordering the affairs of this lower World; hearing the prayers of the Poor in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, being merciful to thoſe who call daily upon him; rejoycing the ſouls of his Servants, and ſaving all ſuch as put their truſt in him. And <hi>David</hi> perhaps having an eye to this, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes his <hi>Pſalter</hi> with this affectionate Exhortation; <hi>let every thing that hath breath praiſe the Lord:</hi> And none can be thought worthy to live, or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the breath of life, who does not chearfully exerciſe himſelf in praying to, and praiſing the Almighty.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:41876:14"/>
            <p>Which ſhews the Univerſality, as well as Neceſſity, of Prayer, and that it is the Duty not only of this or that ſort of men, but of all. For if any ſhould vainly pretend to be excus'd from pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this homage to God, it muſt be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe they are too <hi>holy</hi> or too <hi>great,</hi> either they are ſo <hi>good</hi> as not to need to pray, or ſo <hi>great</hi> that it is below them.</p>
            <p>But no man by reaſon of his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs can be free from this duty; for thoſe who have been moſt eminent for this divine quality, have been alſo moſt eminent for Devotion. And of this you have an unqueſtionable inſtance in our Saviour, who was ſuperlatively eminent for all heavenly perfections, and imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate both by nature and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For he was both born and liv'd without ſin. And yet it is recorded of this moſt heavenly, divine perſon. That in the days of his fleſh, whilſt he was yet in the world, in the courſe of his obedience and humiliation, and not arriv'd to the glorious and ſpiritual ſtate of the celeſtial life, Heb. 5.7. <hi>He did
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41876:14"/>offer up prayers and ſupplications with ſtrong crying and tears, unto him that was able to ſave him from death, and was heard in that he fear'd,</hi> or as it is in the Greek, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>for his piety.</hi> Here the Eternal Son, becoming Man, made his ſubmiſſive Petition to his Eternal Father, either to free him from that direful paſſage to death, or to ſtrengthen and bear him up in the horrible terrors, conflicts and agonies, that therein he met with; and that being dead, he would reſtore him to life, and not to let him continue in the grave, but to raiſe him thence, and ſend back his ſpirit into his body. And God heard and granted his deſire. For the third day after his burial, Chriſt roſe from the dead, and God gave him back that ſpirit which on the Croſs he ſo affectionately recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended into his hands, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.46.</p>
            <p>And as by this plain example of Chriſt's praying, you may clearly ſee that no mans ſanctity can excuſe him from doing doing the like, ſo in the next place no man is freed from praying
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41876:15"/>upon the ſcore of his grandeur or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Greatneſs. This was evident in <hi>David,</hi> who at the ſame time he wore the <hi>Royal Diadem,</hi> did not neglect the <hi>hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Cenſor,</hi> but conſtantly offer'd unto God the Incenſe of Prayer. And for his diligence and aſſiduity in this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred office, he gain'd, as ſome think, the glorious character of being a <hi>Man after God's own heart,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.14. And indeed all good men have ever thought it their duty, and made it their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, to worſhip God by Prayer. And even bad men too have been of the ſame judgment. For they likewiſe have own'd it to be their obligation thus to ſerve God. And whenever they perform'd Prayer as a Duty to him, without doubt they were accepted of him. <hi>Saul</hi> pray'd for a deciſion by lots, and God granted his requeſt, but it had like to have coſt him the life of his <hi>Son,</hi> and the revolt of his <hi>Subjects,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.41, 42. Which ſhows That God do's ſometimes hear the prayers of the wicked, but then it is in <hi>juſtice,</hi> and not in <hi>mercy,</hi> as will appear in due place.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:41876:15"/>
            <p>And now ſeeing Prayer is a ſpecial and principal part of God's worſhip, you muſt own it to be indiſpenſibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd of you, ſo long as you think it your duty to worſhip God. He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and you muſt diſcharge it: your obedience herein is above all things moſt acceptable to God, and will be beſt rewarded by him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The neceſſity of Prayer, as it is made to be the means of obtaining what we want, and of conveying a bleſſing on what we enjoy.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WAnt is commonly ſaid to be the Mother of Prayer, ſo that if you want nothing, you need uſe prayer no otherwiſe than as it is an expreſſion of your <hi>Duty,</hi> and a diſcharge of the <hi>worſhip</hi> you owe to God. But if you ſtand in need of any thing, you can never ſolidly hope to receive it, but by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41876:16"/>the mediation of Prayer; For God has appointed it as the proper means to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his bleſſings. And all thoſe Texts which require Prayer as a <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>homage</hi> belonging to God, do at the ſame time propound it as a <hi>means</hi> to gain his favour in the relief of your wants, and bleſſing what you have.</p>
            <p>But here I expect to find you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting, That tho' Prayer be undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably a part of religious Worſhip which none ought to neglect, yet you think it needleſs to the obtaining a ſupply of your neceſſities; becauſe God needs not your prayers to inform him of your wants, nor to move him to relieve them.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, God needs not your prayers to inform him of your wants; For ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.8. <hi>He knows what things you have need of before you ask him:</hi> which words ſhew, that Prayer is not needful in order to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form God, who by reaſon of his infinite knowledge, can be ignorant of nothing; but they reſpect thoſe who at our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41876:16"/>being upon Earth, were wont to lengthen out their Prayers with vain repetitions and idle Tautologies, thinking they ſhould have their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions the ſooner granted for the ſake of the multitude of words uſed therein: whereas Our Lord aſſures them, that our heavenly Father was not to be wrought upon by their long prayers, and their much ſpeaking, and that ſuch were altogether uſeleſs in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to inform him of mens minds and wants, as fully knowing them without being told. Chriſt was ſo far from abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing, that he eſtabliſhes the uſe of prayer, when he taught his Diſciples how they might pray aright. To which end he gave them a moſt abſolute com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive Form of Prayer: which he enjoyn'd them both to uſe and imitate. Which form bears his Name, and from him is call'd the <hi>Lord's-Prayer.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I ſhall have occaſion to mind you in another place.</p>
            <p>As to the other branch of your Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection which makes Prayers unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to move God to relieve your wants,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41876:17"/>
               <hi>becauſe of his being ready</hi> to do it <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> them, there needs no more to be ſaid to it, but only to deſire you to conſider, That tho' God is naturally inclin'd to be gracious, and ready to give more than either you deſire or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, yet he has been pleas'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That he will not give without asking. And it ſufficiently demonſtrates his goodneſs and bounty to give to them that ask, and to open to them that knock. And tho' goodneſs is eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to God, and that it is his nature and property to open his hand and fill his creatures, yet ſtill he expects you ſhould addreſs your requeſts to him, if not to move his goodneſs to relieve your wants, yet to ſhew you are ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of them: and that you believe he alone is able to give ſupply. Beſides, in every prayer you acknowledge your dependence on God, that you are his Beads-man, live upon his alms, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to receive nothing at his hands, but what you ſeek for by humble and diligent prayer.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:41876:17"/>
            <p>But then again, ſuppoſe Want, (as hath been already obſerv'd) is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Prayer, and prayer the means to have our wants ſupply'd; ſuppoſe at the ſame time you had no want to be ſupply'd, and that you could tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, <hi>I am rich and increas'd with goods and have need of nothing,</hi> Rev. 3.17. ſuppoſe you were able to ſtretch your fancy as far as to imagine an All-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency in your ſelf, and that you were ſet above the reach of indigence; yet ſtill you have need to pray, that God would ſanctify the things you poſſeſs. <hi>For every creature of God is ſanctified by the word and prayer,</hi> 1 Tim: 4.5. Theſe two are requir'd to make all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures lawful for your uſe, and to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you happy in their enjoyment. For firſt, the <hi>Word</hi> permits you a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the uſe of all the Creatures: God therein having remov'd the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, and taken down the old par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition-wall which ſtood between clean and unclean beaſts, and repeal'd the Law concerning forbidden meats. To the repeal of which Law Chriſt had an
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41876:18"/>eye, when he ſaid, <hi>That which goes into the man</hi> (that which is eaten and drunk) <hi>is not that which defiles a man.</hi> And in S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Viſion, Chriſtians are taught to call nothing Common or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean.</p>
            <p>And as the <hi>Word</hi> allows you an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrain'd uſe of all the creatures, ſo Prayer ſanctifies them to your uſe, by obtaining the divine Bleſſing upon them. For whatſoever by the means of prayer you receive from the bountiful hand of heaven, by the ſame means you receive Grace rightly to imploy them, which is that I call a <hi>bleſſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Prayer do's not only obtain a bleſſing upon your dayly food, and the things of this preſent life, but likewiſe on the things relating to the life to come. For the Divine Ordinances which are the means of ſalvation, will never anſwer their end, unleſs God water them from above, and make them proſperous and ſucceſsful. And yet you have no reaſon to expect this bleſſing, unleſs you ſeek it by prayer from him, who alone has power to give it. You muſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41876:18"/>ſeek this bleſſing I ſay only from God, excluſively of all others: which to make out (becauſe the practice of ſome is very much to the contrary) ſhall be the Subject of the next Chapter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Prayer is to be made only unto God.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOU are not ignorant who they are that mantain and practiſe the worſhip of Saints, and pretend to excuſe it by ſaying, <q rend="inline">That the worſhip they give the Saints is of another kind than that which they give unto God.</q> But ſince the Apoſtle forbids us to <hi>call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any in whom we do not believe,</hi> Rom. 10.14. that is, not to pray to any who is not fit to be the object of our Faith and Truſt; and God alone being fit for this, to him alone you ought to make your prayers. But if you will give that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to another which belongs only to God, you transfer his worſhip to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41876:19"/>Creature, which is a moſt aggravating Sacrilege and Injuſtice.</p>
            <p>It is a general received doctrine, That no ſenſible or material ſacrifices, ſuch as were under the Law, are now to be offer'd unto God under the Goſpel, yet all grant that the ſpiritual ſacrifice of Praiſe and Thanks-giving, is ſtill to be offer'd to him, and that to offer this to any other is a derogation from his Glory; and quite contrary to his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, who ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed ſome of the Fathers are thought to have favour'd the Worſhip and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Saints, becauſe they deſir'd the <hi>Holy Men,</hi> whoſe memories they ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated, to joyn with them in their prayers: Yet the expreſſions uſed by them on ſuch occaſions may by any impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Reader be plainly found to be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>flights</hi> of <hi>fancy,</hi> and Wiſhes, than Prayers, and ſavour more of luxurian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Style and Harangue than Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:41876:19"/>
            <p>It is notorious that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> requires her Members to make Vows and offer Incenſe to the Saints: To worſhip their Reliques and Images: To believe that through their help and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance God's benefits are obtain'd; and that for the ſake of their Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, Grace and Merit, he beſtows many favours on mankind. But grant that this were true, and that by reaſon of the benefits you receive by the Saints, you ought to pray to them; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you do this, you ought to be well aſſur'd, that thoſe are really and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly Saints, to whom you are to pray: and that they already enjoy the preſence of God; both which are neceſſary (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven according to the Romaniſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) to warrant your Invocation of them.</p>
            <p>Before you invoke the Saints, you are likewiſe to be well aſſur'd that they can and will hear you, that they know the Wants and State of men upon earth, and are mindful of them; and at leiſure to obtain the things that are pray'd for. Now, to ſay the Saints know all mens
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41876:20"/>Neceſſities, and are ready in all places, and at all times, to ſupply them, is to equal them with God, and to make them as Almighty, Omniſcient, Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as himſelf. Which is a Concluſion the <hi>Papiſts</hi> would be loth to grant, tho' they hold Premiſes na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally tending to it.</p>
            <p>But let the <hi>Papiſt's</hi> Opinions be in this caſe what they pleaſe, it is your happineſs to be of that Communion which teaches you to direct your Prayers only to God; who you are well aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, knows all your Wants, and is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and able to relieve them. The Scripture ſaith expreſly, <hi>that Chriſt is the only mediator with God, and that he gave himſelf a ranſom for all,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.5.6. The office of Saviour and Mediator are two things which muſt neceſſarily be joyn'd together; ſo that he who is the one, is the other alſo. Now ſeeing there is but one Saviour, there is alſo but one Mediator: and that is Chriſt. There is but one God, and he is the Creator of all, and wills and deſigns the good of all; and there is but one
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41876:20"/>Peace-maker God and Man, namely Chriſt, who has taken upon him our Common Nature, and in it dyed for all whoſe Nature he took. He laid down his Life, and pour'd out his Blood, to reſcue Mankind out of an evil State, and commands all that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with him in humane Nature, to come unto God only through <hi>him.</hi> God having no where appointed any other interceſſors beſides him. Which conſideration moved the Church, ever ſince it was call'd Chriſtian, to offer up her Prayers only in the name of Chriſt, and to conclude them in this Form, <hi>Through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Keep therefore to the Doctrine of the Church to which you belong, and which obliges you to pray only to God, and in her 22d. Article cenſures all praying to any elſe, <hi>To be a fooliſh thing, vainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and grounded upon no warrant of Scripture, but rather contrary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:41876:21"/>
            <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Some uncommon Conſiderations to ſtir you up to the Holy exerciſe of Prayer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere is not any one part of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Worſhip, which is more ſtrictly commanded by the Laws of God, or more highly recommended by the practice of Holy Men, than that of Prayer. This carries with it the greater Beauty and Luſtre, and in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects is of greateſt uſe and benefit. And yet notwithſtanding all this, there are not many things wherein (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) you may find your ſelf more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, cool and unactive, than in Prayer. And therefore the better to quicken you up to this Sacred Office, I here preſent you with ſome leſs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Conſiderations to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And (1.) Conſider that by your diligence in Prayer and conſtant cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon God, you become his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer, and ſuffer him not to be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41876:21"/>unmindful of you. And indeed he can no more be forgetful of ſuch as importune him with their Prayers, than a Mother can forget her ſucking Child. But if a Mother ſhould be ſo unnatural as to ſtop her ears to the Infants cry, yet God will hearken unto the cry of his Children, and give them, if not what they particularly deſire, yet what he knows to be moſt for their good. It is not ſafe for you to conclude of his kindneſs towards you, by his not ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily granting your Requeſts. For they that are deareſt to him, may often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with great difficulty work out thoſe bleſſings, which fall into the Mouths of the Careleſs. <q rend="inline">And the Wiſe diſpoſer of all things, knows it fit to hold his beſt Servants ſhort of thoſe Favours which they ſue for: but then it is for the tryal of their Faith, or the exerciſe of their Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or the encreaſe of their Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, or the doubling of their Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</q> And when he withholds his Benefits for a while from his humbleſt Suppliants, yet he does not forget them.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41876:22"/>However, if he were capable of forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any one, as he is not (and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of thoſe that pray unto him) yet frequent application is of the like nature with the importunity we uſe to one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, when we want to be reminded and have our Memory refreſh'd. It is hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a continual converſe with God, as humbly to let him know, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did the Angel with whom he ſtrove, that we will not ſuffer him to leave till he is graciouſly pleas'd to bleſs us.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) All pious Chriſtians, according to S. <hi>Paul, have their converſation in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> Phil. 3.20. Matth. 6.20, 21. it is their Property and Glory to live here below as if they were above: they bend all their Thoughts and Deſires prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to Heaven, and tho' their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are on Earth, yet their Affections are where Chriſt ſits at the right hand of God. Now, there is no readier way for you to have your Converſation in Heaven, than by continually ſending up your Soul thither in fervent Prayer. For by this you pierce the Clouds, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41876:22"/>have acceſs to the throne of Divine Mercy, and hold correſpondence with the Almighty Maker and Governor of the Univerſe. When your Soul is not preſs'd down with earthly, heavy Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but by a pure and holy Life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes light and Ethereal, then it nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly mounts up to the things on high, and may be ſaid to ſoar above the low, creeping Concerns of this impure World, and to have its Converſation in Heaven. And by the force of pious Deſires it aſcends to the bleſſed Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons above, whence you look for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And if this be fully conſider'd, 'twill be enough to endear Devotion to your choice, and to oblige your care of ſo Seraphic a performance.</p>
            <p>In the Third place, Conſider that at the laſt general Judgment your Prayers ſhall come up for a memorial before God, and be both acknowledged and rewarded by him. Then will the Judge of the whole Earth own all devout Souls for his, and in the moſt literal ſenſe make good what ought, as far
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41876:23"/>as in us lies, to be daily verified in this World, <hi>That he is greatly to be feared in the Aſſembly of the Saints, and to be had in Reverence of all thoſe that are round about him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Sacred Hiſtory of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> you read of <hi>Cornelius</hi> a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelyte of the <hi>Jews;</hi> one who worſhipped the true God, tho' uncircumcis'd, <hi>That he gave much alms to the poor, and pray'd to God alway:</hi> Acts 10. He was cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable and bountiful to the indigent, and a conſtant obſerver of the ſet times of Prayer. And his Alms and Prayers were ſo pleaſing to God, that they brought down no ordinary bleſſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: for of a Jewiſh Proſelyte God made him a Chriſtian Convert. By which ſingle inſtance you may diſcern the particular regard Heaven has for thoſe who conſcientiouſly obſerve ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Times of Prayer, and joyn Works of Charity with Devotion. That ſuch are bleſſed of the Lord, and ſhall not fail of reaping the Fruit thereof in due ſeaſon, if they faint not.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:41876:23"/>
            <p>Conſider in the laſt place the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſatisfaction which from Prayer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crews to the beſt and worthieſt Powers of your Soul. All thinking men ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, That the <hi>Underſtanding</hi> and <hi>Will</hi> (which are your principal Faculties) meet with a ſenſible Pleaſure and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, when they are employ'd about the nobleſt of their proper Objects. Now, Truth is the moſt proper object of the Underſtanding, and God is the nobleſt Truth, and ſeeing that in Prayer the <hi>Mind</hi> is employ'd in the Contemplation of him, it cannot miſs of Delight and Pleaſure, nor fares it otherwiſe with the Will, the proper Object whereof is what we call Good (either real or in appearance.) Now in Prayer the Will is ſuppos'd to be fixt upon God who is Goodneſs it ſelf; (all thoſe Excellencies which are ſcatter'd among the Creatures and denominate them to be good, and all which put together are but few and ſmall in compariſon of the ſupreme Good) do all concentre in a ſuperlative degree in him to whom we pray; ſo that the mind muſt needs receive a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41876:24"/>delight, as being thereby conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant about the moſt excellent of the things that properly belong to them. But beſides all this, there is a great ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction accrewing to the Soul through the means of Prayer, by reaſon of that pious Familiarity which therein it enjoys with God. Can there be a greater ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to your Rational part, than to have the liberty of unloading all your Perplexities and Fears, Scruples and Doubts, into the boſom of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty? Is it poſſible that any thing ſhould bring more eaſe to a pained Mind, than freely to make known unto the Lord, not only your Frailties, but even your worſt wilful Sins, and that too with aſſurance of their Remiſſion, if they are truly repented of and entirely forſaken? That God, the only Maker, Preſerver, and Univerſal Monarch of the World, ſhould admit ſinful Duſt and Aſhes to approach him, and in Prayer to converſe with him, is not only the higheſt Satisfaction and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, but the greateſt Dignity and Vouchſafement whereof a Mortal can be capable.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:41876:24"/>
            <p>When Gods Wrath was ſo incens'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that he reſolved to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them, he could not do it whilſt <hi>Moſes</hi> Pray'd for them, and therefore he bad him give over his Praying, and to let him alone, that he might exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Diſpleaſure he had againſt that ſtiffnecked People, which by <hi>Moſes</hi>'s in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion was reſtrain'd. And though <hi>Moſes</hi> grants that there were great Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Cauſes for God to deſtroy them, yet he ſhews alſo that there were greater for God to ſpare them. By their Sins they deſerv'd Deſtruction, but yet God's Glory was concern'd in their Preſervation, leſt otherwiſe the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> ſhould ſay; <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>For miſchief did he bring them out to ſlay them in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and to conſume them from the face of the earth, Exod.</hi> 32.12.14.</q> And <hi>Moſes</hi>'s interceſſion for <hi>Iſrael</hi> was ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing, that God repented of the Evil which he thought to do unto his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Not that there could be in God a proper Repentance, as it ſignifies a ſorrow for a Fault committed, and an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of his Mind toward the ſame
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41876:25"/>ſubject: but by this word <hi>(repenting)</hi> taken from Men, is ſignified an aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God's will and liking towards a thing which of Good is become Evil. But that which is chiefly here to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark'd, is, the force Prayer has with the Alwiſe Creator, in that by it <hi>Moſes</hi> moved God to avert his Judgements, and to appeaſe the Anger he had juſtly conceiv'd againſt his People. It was Prayer that hinder'd <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Ruin, and it is ſtill the beſt Inſtrument to fetch down the greateſt Bleſſings: for <hi>it pierces the clouds</hi> ſaith <hi>Ben-Sirach, and will not turn away till the higheſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it, Ecclus.</hi> 35.17.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">You would think your ſelf an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Man if you could get one certain means of helping you to whatever you wanted, tho' it coſt you never ſo much pains and labour to get it.</q> Prayer is this certain means, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fails of bringing you, if not all that you think you want, yet all that you really want, or all that God ſees fit for you. And conſidering in what continual want you are of receiving ſomething or
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41876:25"/>other from that bountiful hand which only is able to ſupply all Wants, it were an unaccountable carriage to neglect that which alone can procure it.</p>
            <p>Nor is there any ſuch uneaſineſs in the exerciſe of Prayer, as may diſhearten you from its performance. For if there be any uneaſineſs therein, it ariſes not from the nature of the Duty, but the untowardneſs of your own Heart. If you would refine and purge that from all Earthly and Carnal Thoughts, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to put it into an Heavenly, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual frame, and accuſtom it to Prayer, all uneaſineſs therein would wear off, and for Pain you would find a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Delight and Pleaſure. For not only your beſt Faculties are employ'd about the nobleſt of their proper Objects in Prayer (as was ſaid) but it alſo brings you near to him who is the Source and Spring of all Felicity; which muſt needs yield a great Delight to Hearts which are not diſtemper'd, and like a ſick Palate cannot reliſh the moſt pleaſant Food. But Prayer being a Spiritual Duty, is not to be taſted by a Mind that is Carnal,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41876:26"/>therefore if your Affections be ſet ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the Delights of the Fleſh, or the Droſs of the World, no wonder if the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Pleaſures of Devotion are inſipid, and that like <hi>Iſrael,</hi> you prefer Fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pots before Milk and Honey, and leave the <hi>Quails</hi> and <hi>Manna,</hi> for <hi>Onions</hi> and <hi>Garlick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You will not, I hope, account theſe things unworthy of your Thoughts, nor wilfully make your ſelf comfortleſs, by ſuffering either Employments or Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures to thruſt them out of your Mind: But rather make uſe of them to ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon your Delights, and ſweeten your Troubles, and interpoſe themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt you and the World; that ſo your Life may be happy, and your Death welcome.</p>
            <p>I know you have better Monitors, and carry the beſt about you, in your boſom. And if what I write be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, yet it argues my Affection, and diſcharges the Duty of Friendſhip. My Prayers are better than my Counſels, and both are hearty and unfained for your good. God proſper your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41876:26"/>and make you happy in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of what you now receive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Lord, we beſeech thee mercifully to hear us, and grant that we, to whom thou haſt given an hearty deſire to Pray, may by thy Mighty Aid be Defended and Comforted in all Dangers and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, through Jeſus Chriſt Our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Preparation to</hi> Prayer.</head>
            <p>HAving giving you an account of the Nature of <hi>Prayer,</hi> I come next to ſhew what is requir'd to render your Prayers acceptable, and ſo prevent the praying amiſs: And the firſt thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quifite to this end is the Preparing and Fitting of your ſelf for ſo excellent a Performance. That there is ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration expected at your hands, you may learn both from Reaſon and Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41876:27"/>from whence all that is Solid and truly Argumentative is to be had for the proof of any Poſition.</p>
            <p>And Firſt, Reaſon, or the <hi>Light</hi> which is Natural and Common to all Men, clearly ſhews you, <hi>That matters of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and importance ought not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, till they be throughly weigh'd;</hi> and it be conſider'd, how they may be beſt manag'd and effected. <hi>He that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to build a houſe, or to make war, ought firſt to ſit down and conſider whether he has ſufficient to carry on the work be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he begins it, leſt having begun and wanting abilities to finiſh, he be</hi> forc'd <hi>to give it over with ſhame and reproach,</hi> Luke 14.28, 29, 30, 31, <hi>&amp;c</hi> Few things ſucceed well which are not firſt well conſidered. Every thing you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake requires a Preparation ſutable to the Undertaking. And in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Prayer you may fetch Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments enough from within your ſelf for an humble Preparation to diſcharge it. For when you ſeriouſly reflect upon your own Vileneſs, the dreadful Majeſty of Heaven to which you are to Pray,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41876:27"/>and the fearful effects of not Praying aright, you muſt be far gone in ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity and ſenſeleſneſs, if you appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend not the neceſſity of preparing your ſelf for this Duty.</p>
            <p>No man will ſolicit a favour at the hands of one of like Paſſion with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, without uſing the due forms of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication. Would you not eſteem it a piece of egregious rudeneſs to addreſs an <hi>Earthly Potentate</hi> in a <hi>Style</hi> and <hi>Mode,</hi> which is contrary to the Cuſtom, and not done with that Grace as is uſual on ſuch occaſions. Common Senſe directs you to approach thoſe who are your <hi>Superiours</hi> either in <hi>Condition,</hi> or <hi>Power,</hi> or both, in ſuch a ſort as becomes their Station and yours. Reaſon is a Law againſt Indecency, as well as againſt groſſer Immoralities. So that you need no clearer Light then that within, to ſhew you with what careful prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redneſs you are to ſpeak unto God by Prayer, and hold an holy Converſe with him, in that beſt of Religious Duties.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:41876:28"/>
            <p>Will any man of either Modeſty or Diſcretion venture to utter himſelf <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore</hi> concerning Matters of higheſt importance in a grave and learned Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly? Will he not rather (if he may) chooſe to come prepared, and compoſe, and weigh every Word and Period, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ventures to ſpeak, leſt he expoſe himſelf by any rude and indigeſted Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; this would be but a becoming Piece of Reſpect at leaſt, and the want of it be condemn'd as no ſmall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption; Now in the caſe before us, the reaſon of the thing is only ſo much ſtronger than it can be put in any worldly Concerns, as there is ſo much more of awe due to the Perſon we are to ſpeak to, and the Buſineſs we come upon is of far greater Moment than any thing that is meerly Temporal can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to. You that Fray are but a Worm, Duſt, a Shadow, a Bubble, Nothing, nay worſe, ſinful, polluted and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: He to whom you Pray is the Lord of Heaven and Earth, who is able eternally to deſtroy your Soul and Body in Hell. The things you may Pray for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41876:28"/>are not of an inferiour, but of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Moment, even the Salvation of your Soul: Grace in this Life and Glory in the next.</p>
            <p>And when you have maturely conſider'd theſe things, I leave you to make your own Concluſion as to the Preparation now ſpoken of; And whether Reaſon do's not convince you of its Neceſſity.</p>
            <p>But if your great Oracle, Reaſon, were Dumb in this caſe, yet the Scriptures are plain and expreſs to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>They teach you not to come before God without having firſt fitted your ſelf for ſo dreadful a <hi>Preſence.</hi> And this you may collect from God's Command to <hi>Aaron;</hi> which was, that neither he nor his Sons ſhould Enter upon Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, till they had waſh't their hands and feet in the Laver appointed for that end, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. A Ceremony that among other things, did certainly imply, that all ought Piouſly to compoſe and order themſelves for the Celebration of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Doubts, and to put away all Filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs both of Fleſh and Spirit, e're they did enter upon ſo Momentous a Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41876:29"/>You read in <hi>Eſay</hi> 1. that God would not look upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they ſpread out their hands unto him, (which was an ancient manner of Praying) nor hearken when they made many Prayers, becauſe their Hands were full of Blood, and their Actions full of Injuſtice. But if <hi>they would waſh and make themſelves clean, and put away the evil of their doings, and retract their faults,</hi> then he would incline his Ear to their Supplications, and be found of them when they ſought unto him. But till this was done, all their Sacrifices, Prayers, and Oblations, were to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Whilſt <hi>Iſrael lov'd to wander and would not refrain their feet;</hi> whilſt they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in their Vices and would not give over their wicked Courſes, God did not only reject their own Prayers, but alſo the Prayers that others made in their behalf. For he poſitively for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad the Prophet to pray for them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.16. and 14.12, 11. Declaring, that he would not hear their Cry when they Faſted, nor accept them when they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd Burnt Offerings and Oblations.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41876:29"/>And thoſe Cruel Princes that <hi>pluck't the Skin of the People, and the Fleſh from their Bones; who chopt them in pieces for the Pot, and as fleſh for the Caldron, when they cry'd unto the Lord, he would not hear them, becauſe they were wicked in their doings: Mich.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4. <hi>Though they cry in mine ears,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>with a loud voice,</hi> yet <hi>I will not hear them, Ezek.</hi> 8.18. <hi>Mine eye ſhall not ſpare, neither will I have pity:</hi> You have then no hope that God ſhould accept your Services, whilſt you continue Impenitent. Your Heart muſt be furniſh'd with ſincere Piety, if you expect your Prayers ſhould be regarded in God's ſight, or that any other part of Worſhip ſhould be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and welcom to him. Without Repentance all the Religious Acts you can poſſibly execute, are but Illuſion and Hypocriſie; inward Wickedneſs hidden under the Cloak and Viſard of outward Sanctity. Till therefore you give Glory to God by a free Confeſſion of your Sins, and by a lively Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion fly to his Mercy, you can neither feel the effects of Pardon, nor the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41876:30"/>of your Prayers. Whilſt your Silver is Droſs and your Wine mixt with Water; whilſt your Life and Actions (that ſhould be Pure) continue Corrupt and Degenerate, all you do in Religion in ſtead of Appeaſing, will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe the Divine Diſpleaſure.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Preparation to Prayer practiſed by the</hi> Jews, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AND what is now ſpoken concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this Preparation, is no novel or upſtart Doctrine, but an ancient Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Truth, Taught and Practis'd by Men of all Religions, and rejected by none but the Lewd and Miſcreant.</p>
            <p>And firſt, as to the Antient <hi>Jews, Ariſtaeus</hi> reports, that it was their Cuſtom to Waſh before they Pray'd, <hi>Hiſt.</hi> 72. And the modern <hi>Jews,</hi> (living in the Eaſtern Countries) obſerve the ſame cuſtom of Waſhing, as a Preparative to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41876:30"/>Prayer and reading the <hi>Shemaah.</hi> And no doubt they do this in imitation of the Prieſts, who enter'd not upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming any Religious Office in the Sanctuary, unleſs they had firſt Waſh'd. And it was with reſpect to this Cuſtom, that <hi>David</hi> would not come to the Altar, till he had waſht his Hands in Innocency; that is, till he had prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelf to Worſhip God: being well aſſur'd that he was not worthy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Divine Protection, or any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Anſwer to the Prayers, wherein he did not joyn Purity to Devotion, and had a Heart as clean as the Hands he had waſht: And that his Thoughts and Actions were as purified as his Body. And tho' it was common with the <hi>Jews</hi> in any ſolemn Buſineſs to waſh their Hands in proteſtation of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, yet this Ceremony was eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially uſed before they ſaid their Prayers: Which ſhew'd the great eſteem they had for that Duty, and that they thought it of ſuch Holineſs and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as that it could not be rightly perform'd, without a Preparation an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41876:31"/>thereunto. And this you may further collect from the ſeveral Rules preſcrib'd by the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd by the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they come to Pray. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Maſters forbad any to enter the Temple with Shooes on their Feet. Which Prohibition they founded on thoſe Words of God to <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Put thy ſhooes off thy feet, for the place whereon thou ſtandeſt is holy ground;</hi> which command was alſo given to <hi>Joſhua</hi> (5.15.) <hi>by the captain of the Lords hoſt.</hi> God does not bid them to put off their Shooes as if the Ground whereon they ſtood were Holy, by an internal or perpetual Quality, but becauſe of God's Preſence, which he was pleas'd at that time, in that place, in a more eſpecial manner to exhibit. And from this injunction given to theſe two Worthies, <hi>Solomon</hi> likely gave that General Rule, namely, that every one ſhould take heed to his Feet when he enter'd the Houſe of God. Which Text the <hi>Targum</hi> explains thus, <q rend="inline">Thou Son of Man, take heed to thy Feet, when thou entreſt into the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41876:31"/>to Pray, and go not thither full of thy Sins unrepented of. And be not as Fools who offer Sacrifices for their Sins, and yet turn not from them.</q> Only Penitents then are fit to come to the Houſe of Prayer, and to be Suppliants at the Throne of Grace. Every one is to put off his Shooes, to abandon his Sins when he comes unto God; to take heed to his Feet and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach him with all poſſible Reverence. Under the Law no man had liberty to come into the Congregation, who had touch'd any Unclean thing, till he was ſprinkl'd with Water by the Prieſt. And under the Goſpel there is no coming unto God, without <hi>having</hi> your <hi>heart ſprinkl'd from an evil Conſcience, and your body waſh't with pure water, Heb.</hi> 10.22.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Maſters forbad any to enter the Temple with Duſt on their Feet; meaning thereby, That all Earthly and Worldly Affections, Thoughts and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, were to be ſhaken off and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged by them, who come to offer Spiritual Holy Services unto God. The
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41876:32"/>
               <hi>Jews</hi> were alſo injoyn'd not to bring with them into the Sanctuary any of thoſe Tools and Inſtruments uſed by them in their Civil Trades and Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: by which they were alſo mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to leave behind them whatſoever might in the leaſt ſuggeſt any Earthly Concern, Worldly Notion, or Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, whilſt they were at God's Houſe; leſt they ſhould be diſturb'd or diverted in Devotion.</p>
            <p>Nor were the <hi>Jews</hi> ſingular in this particular, or the only People that were careful thus to Prepare themſelves for Prayer. For the <hi>Mahumedans</hi> (who took many of their Rites from the <hi>Jews</hi>) are very preciſe in Preparing themſelves for the <hi>Moſchs</hi> or <hi>Giamma's,</hi> the places of their Publick Worſhip. For they never repair to theſe till they have firſt Waſh't at home; nor do they enter thoſe Solemn Places with their Shooes on. And they are of Opinion, That if they come Unprepared to Prayers, or behave themſelves Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently at them, that they loſe the benefit of their coming. <hi>Cleanlineſs</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41876:32"/>to <hi>Mahumed</hi> is the <hi>Key of Prayer,</hi> and that it is not regarded without it. Under the name of Cleanlineſs, all the Preparatives to Prayer are underſtood. And by Prayer is meant the whole Syſtem of Religious Worſhip. Now, this Cleanlineſs does not only reſpect the Body, but alſo regards the Mind and Converſation: and it implies the putting away of all unlawful Actions, the purging of the Heart from all vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and unworthy Thoughts and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: And they hold that Filthineſs in theſe is a thing moſt offenſive to God; who according to their <hi>Alcoran,</hi> as well as our <hi>Bible,</hi> is of Purer Eyes than to behold the leaſt Defilement.</p>
            <p>And it may well be ſuppos'd that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> will not come behind <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Mahumedans</hi> in this particular: Nor boldly and inconſiderately ruſh upon thoſe holy Duties, which theſe Infidels approach with ſo great Preparedneſs. The Apoſtle adviſes all of his Religion, <hi>to lift up holy</hi> and pure <hi>hands</hi> in Prayer; 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8. By his Apoſtolical Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, he appointed that not only at the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41876:33"/>Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but every where elſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhould Pray with that Ceremony of holding up the hands, joyn'd with Purity of Conſcience and Good Works: And that they ſhould take care, that no doubts or irreſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Mind ſhould hinder the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe or benefit of Prayer. You do but burn <hi>Incenſe</hi> to <hi>Vanity,</hi> and lift up your hands to Heaven to no purpoſe, whilſt you regard Iniquity in your Heart, and your Actions are unjuſt. God will caſt back your Prayers, like dung upon your face, and reject both them and your Perſon, when you tread his Courts, and at the ſame time hate to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd. <hi>God hears not ſinners, but if any man be his worſhipper, him he heareth,</hi> S. <hi>John</hi> 9.31. <hi>His eyes are over the righteous and his ears are open to their Prayers: but his face is againſt them that do evil; Pſal.</hi> 34.15. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12. <hi>God looks kindly on his obedient ſervants, but he ſets himſelf as an enemy againſt the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately wicked. He is nigh to good men and hears their Prayers, but their Prayer is an abomination unto him who turn their
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41876:33"/>ears from hearing the Law. Prov.</hi> 28.9.15.29. The humble dutiful Soul implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God's aſſiſtance, is ſure to receive it, in kind or in equivalence.</p>
            <p>But the Texts of Scripture declaring the Prayers of Sinners to be ineffectual, are to be underſtood of none but Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent ſinners, who ſtubbornly walk in the Ways of their own Hearts, and do that which is Right in their own Eyes: who either wilfully continue in their Impieties, or retain a kindneſs for them. It is not then your having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Sin, and your ſenſe of ſome Guilt being upon you, that ought to hinder your Praying. For you muſt Pray the rather that God may remit and pardon the ſins you have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For if you are humbly minded, and ſincerely chang'd from Bad to Good; if you loath and forſake your evil Ways, and with a broken and contrite Heart grieve for your Offences, you then are one whoſe cry God will hear, and <hi>whoſe tears he will put into his bottle,</hi> and not ſuffer a Drop falling from the eye of a Penitent to be as Water ſpilt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41876:34"/>upon the ground: <hi>He will hear your cry, and deliver your ſoul from death. He will recover your feet from falling, that you may walk before him in the light of the living: Pſal.</hi> 116.8, 9.13. He will give you ſpace and opportunity to live, and acceptably to ſerve him. He will hear your Prayers when you come unto him without the love of your Sins about you, or purpoſes to continue in them.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Noah</hi> came out of the <hi>Ark,</hi> in which, ſaith one, he had long been <hi>Buried</hi> not Dead, his firſt Care was to Build an Altar unto the Lord, and to take of every Clean Beaſt, and of every Clean Fowl to offer in Burnt-Offerings. And the Lord ſmelt a ſweet Savour; he took notice of the Purity of <hi>Noah</hi>'s heart, and accepted of his Actions, and ſhew'd himſelf pleas'd with his Holy Intentions. But that which herein ſeems to be moſt obſervable, and to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, was <hi>Noah</hi>'s great Induſtry and Care for the right offering of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice; And this was ſeen in his Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding an Altar, and making Choice of ſuch Beaſts and Birds as were fit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41876:34"/>to be Offered. Now, Prayer is your beſt Sacrifice, which in Imitation of <hi>Noah,</hi> you are to offer unto the Lord with great Preparedneſs. For the want of this will betray in you a Prophane temper of Spirit, and a lack of a juſt Eſteem and Reverence for God and his Service. And therefore according to <hi>Siracides,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Before thou prayeſt prepare thy ſelf, and be not as one that tempteth the Lord: Ecclus,</hi> 18.23.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Let the Clean Beaſts and Birds of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd by <hi>Noah,</hi> mind you of keeping your Soul Clean and Pure from all wicked Reſolutions and Affections; and to appear before the Lord empty of all Sinful Habits and Intentions. And let no Envy, Hatred, Malice, or any Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs, lodge in your Heart. For no Luſts of Carnal Uncleanneſs, no Filthineſs of Spirit, no unſatiable and inordinate Love of the World, muſt poſſeſs your Soul when you lift it up to God. For you can never perform aright the great Duty of Prayer, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs your Heart be Penitent, and your Affections Pure. The Holineſs of your
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41876:35"/>Perſon makes the Prayer Holy, and the ſavour of your Sacrifice ſweet in God's Noſtrils. But if any wilful Sin lyes at the Door, it ſtops the paſſage of Prayer, and hinders it from being gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly heard. Put away then the evil of your Doings, and remove your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Impurity, and be wholly Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to God's Service, <hi>And then ſhall your Prayer be ſet forth in his ſight, as the incenſe, and the lifting up of your hands, ſhall be as the Evening ſacrifice. Pſal.</hi> 141.1.2. For though you ſhould outwardly appear never ſo Pure, and ſo carry your ſelf that no Spot can be ſeen upon the Surface of your Actions, <hi>Yet if you regard iniquity in your heart, the Lord will not hear you; Pſal.</hi> 66.18. So that in ſhort, your Preparation to Prayer conſiſts in your Repentance for all the Sins whereof (upon the moſt diligent Scrutiny) you find your ſelf to be Guilty; for every Sin whereof you do not Repent, will hinder the Power and Efficacy of your Prayer. And it will be with you as it was with <hi>Joſhua,</hi> whoſe Prayer for <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:41876:35"/>God utterly refus'd, <hi>Becauſe they had taken of the thing which was devoted unto him, and which had brought a curſe upon them; Joſh.</hi> 7.10.11.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Graces neceſſary to Prayer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AND when you have thus ſwept the Houſe, and caſt all the Filth and Rubbiſh out of Doors, your next buſineſs is to ſee it Decently Furniſh'd: For you are not only to Cleanſe your Heart from noyſom Luſts and Paſſions, but get it Repleniſh't with ſuch Graces and Vertues, Qualities and Diſpoſitions, as are requir'd to Prayer. Now, Faith is the firſt of theſe Graces, and the Foundation of all the reſt.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the uſe of Faith in Prayer.</head>
               <p>Worſhip, you have heard, is that Great Duty which you owe to God, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41876:36"/>by which in an eſpecial manner you acknowledg his Godhead. And this Worſhip you are to perform both in Soul and Body. For both are his, and in both he will be Glorified and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt. Now, Prayer is the Soul's part of this Worſhip, and is to be made in Faith, or otherwiſe it will not pleaſe God. <hi>He that comes</hi> or prays <hi>to God, muſt believe that he is, and that he is a Rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him.</hi> Which Text implies, That you are not only to acknowledge the Eſſence of God, (which is done by the Infernal Fiends,) but alſo to believe that he will give what you duly beg of him, and bountifully recompence your dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in the Search and Performance of his Will. And believing this, you can find nothing fit to Tempt you to neglect God's Service. And altho' your Sincerity and Faithfulneſs therein ſhould coſt you dear, yet you are aſſured, that whatſoever Pains or Expences you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow in his Service, it will be abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rewarded by your Gracious Maſter. And your Belief of this is the Ground
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41876:36"/>of your Entrance on God's Worſhip, and Perſeverance in it. And as you may beſt ſhew your Faith by your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of Prayer, ſo you may be thought to have little or no Faith, if you are ſeldom or never at your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. But if once your come ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly to believe the Power, Wiſdom, Juſtice and Goodneſs of the Almighty, you can want no motives to Pray to him. There is no Promiſe annext to any Prayer, but what is made in Faith: and for this you have the Authority of our Great Maſter, who told his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <hi>That they ſhould receive all things whatſoever they ask'd in Prayer, if they believ'd; Matth.</hi> 21, 22. Not that Chriſt by thoſe words gave you Toleration to ask whatſoever ſhall come in your fancy; for Prayer muſt be regulated by <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> muſt not go beyond the bounds of the Word. But our Lord forbids you to truſt and confide in your Self, and to rely on your own Strength and Abilities for the getting of what you want; he would have you by Prayer to apply your ſelf to God
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41876:37"/>the Father in the Name of God the Son; and firmly to believe that what you beg in Chriſt's Name, will be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you according to his Word, in S. <hi>Mark</hi> 11.24. <hi>I ſay unto you what things ſoever ye deſire, when ye Pray, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that ye receive them, and ye ſhall have them.</hi> Believing in this place, has reſpect to the Promiſe Chriſt made to all who call upon God in his Name. And it ſignifies your being throughly perſwaded that God will grant the thing you beg of him in the Name of Chriſt, through whom alone your Prayers are Effectual and Prevailing. <hi>If any of you lack wiſdom, let himask of God that giveth to all men liberally, and upbraideth not, and it ſhall be given him: but let him ask in faith, nothing wavering. Jam.</hi> 1.5, 6. If any man pray, let him pray with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to be heard, and with a Mind reſolv'd to ſtick faſt to God, and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly to adhere to the Doctrine and Practice to Chriſtianity. And doing thus he has no reaſon to be Doubtful of the Divine Care and Protection. <hi>The Prayer of Faith ſhall ſave the ſick, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41876:37"/>the Lord ſhall raiſe him up, and if he have committed ſins, they ſhall be forgiven him; Jam.</hi> 5.15.</p>
               <p>Here are Diſplay'd two wonderful Effects of thoſe Prayers which proceed from Faith in Chriſt; Firſt, they prevail with God for the Recovery, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of the Sick to his former Health; unleſs God has purpos'd to diſpoſe of it otherwiſe for the Good of the Infirm, and his own Glory. Next, they ſhall prevail for the Pardon of the Sins, for which he is chaſtiſed of God with Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, if upon his Recovery he amend his Life. But ſtill in granting your Prayers God has reſpect to his own Glory and your Benefit. And when the Granting what you Pray for is Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with either of theſe, he merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully withholds his Hand from giving it. And ſeeing this Faith whereof we now ſpeak, is the Gift of God, humbly beſeech him to pour this moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Gift into your Heart, and to work in you ſuch a Faith as may be as an Hand to receive all his Favours: Be careful not to acquieſce in a dead, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41876:38"/>effectual Faith, but in ſuch a Faith as ſhews its ſelf in good Works; and which inables you to overcome the World, and to conform to his Will in whom you believe,</p>
               <p>To the end that you may Pray a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, take care when you enter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Service, <q rend="inline">to entertain your Mind with the ſerious Thoughts of God's Excellencies and Perfections: That his Mercy is over all his Works and endureth for ever; That he is Faithful, and without all Variableneſs or ſhadow of Change; That his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen;</hi> That he is nigh to all that call upon him faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; and that he will (one way or other) fulfil the Deſires of them that Fear him.</q> With theſe and the like conſiderations, you may vigorate and enliven your Devotions with an Active Faith; and draw near and fall low at his Footſtool, in full Aſſurance that his Ear is open, and his Hand ſtretcht out, to give you the things you long for, or ſome thing elſe, which in his Infinite Wiſdom he knows to be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41876:38"/>better for you. You are not alway to believe, you ſhall certainly receive eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular thing you Pray for: you cannot with any juſt confidence expect what God hath no where promis'd. And tho' he has abſolutely promis'd you all things pertaining to Eternal Life, and Godlineſs; yet as to the things appertaining to this preſent Life, he has limited his promiſe of them; ſo that he will give or withhold them, as he ſees them Neceſſary, Profitable, or Convenient for you. Seeing then that all the Promiſes of God are not of equal Extent, and ſeeing your Faith can go no farther than the Promiſes; you cannot firmly believe, that you ſhall have every particular thing granted you, becauſe you cannot certainly tell, whether this or that will be Beneficial, or Proper for you. For whatever you may imagine or conceive in your own Thoughts, it is God alone that knows that Infallibly, and therefore you cannot be aſſur'd that God will beſtow it on you.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:41876:39"/>
            <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Charity requir'd in Prayer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AND as you are to pray in Faith, ſo likewiſe in Charity. This is a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſive Grace, ready to do good, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it ſelf to all. It takes the whole Race of Mankind into your <hi>Litany,</hi> and obliges you to pray according to our Saviour's Form, which teaches you to beg all the ſame Bleſſings for others, that you beg for you ſelf. All your buſineſs in this Life, next to ſerving God, is to do all the Good you can to your ſelf and others. And ſeeing by reaſon of the narrow and weak condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your Nature, it is not in your Power to do all that is needful, you muſt therefore apply your ſelf to him from whom cometh every good and perfect Gift; praying, that he out of his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite and inexhauſtible Treaſures, would ſupply the Wants of all Men. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every one is in ſome Want or other,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41876:39"/>every one muſt have a ſhare in your Prayers.</p>
            <p>The forgiveneſs of your Treſpaſſes, is that which above all things you have abſolute need to deſire of God; for without this all other Bleſſings would be inſignificant. But you have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to expect God ſhould forgive you your Treſpaſſes, unleſs you forgive Men their Treſpaſſes. In the Petition you make for Pardon of your own Sins, you ſolicit your own Ruine, if you pardon not others their Sins: For in ſaying, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us our Treſpaſſes, as we forgive them that treſpaſs againſt us, you pray God would never pardon you, if you do not pardon others. How can you ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally deſire Forgiveneſs from God, when you deny it to your Neighbour? The great Man in the Goſpel who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave his Servant a conſiderable Sum, when he deſir'd it, charg'd the ſame anew upon him, when he refuſed to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give his Fellow-ſervant a ſmall Debt. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.23. His doing this ſo far provok'd his Lords indignation againſt him, that he gave him up to the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentors.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41876:40"/>And thus will God deal with you, if you deal thus with your Fellow-Chriſtians; who can never ſo far treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs againſt you, as you do againſt God: Who will aſſuredly handle you as you do them. <hi>If you forgive not men their treſpaſſes, your heavenly father will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give you yours; Matth.</hi> 6.15. And as the Goodneſs of God can in nothing be more Evident and Illuſtrious than in readily Forgiving thoſe who beg his Pardon: So there is not any thing in which his Juſtice can be more Equal, than in dealing Severely with thoſe, who deal Severely with their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            <p>It's obſervable, that our Saviour took hold of frequent occaſions to inculcate the Neceſſity of Mutual Charity, and that he made it the Badge whereby his Followers were to be diſtinguiſhed from men of all other Religions. And to the end you might continually remember it, he inſerted it into the Prayer which you are to uſe daily; <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Forgive us our treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, as we forgive them that treſpaſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us;</hi>
               </q>—And with what Face can
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41876:40"/>you look up to the Father of Mercies with this Petition in your Mouth, if you want Compaſſion and Charity? How can you hope to prevail with your Crys and Importunities on God, as long as you have no Bowels your ſelf towards your Neighbour. Remember it is the Rule of Gods Proceedings, <hi>That he ſhall have Judgment without Mercy, who has ſhew'd no Mercy; Jam.</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p>And tho' Prayer be the beſt Sacrifice and the beſt Gift, you can bring to God's Altar, yet it will not be accepted at your hands, if your <hi>Heart</hi> be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, when you come to offer it. There were many things which under the Law would render the beſt of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices rather Offenſive to Almighty God, than be of any Avail to him that offer'd them; and in like manner there is nothing which more effectually at once deſtroys the whole deſign of what is the True and Proper Chriſtian Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, than Uncharitableneſs. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you have any Pique, or Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Variance with your Neighbour, do all that in you lies to be reconcil'd to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41876:41"/>him, before you preſent God with your Supplications. For Chriſt taught you this when he bad him, who brought his Gift to the Prieſt to be offer'd in Atonement for his Sins, that if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member'd he had injur'd any man, he ſhould leave his offering unpreſented, and repair to the perſon he had wrong'd, and to uſe Means to make him Friends with him, and then to come and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat his intended Atonement.</p>
            <p>Every wilful Sin is a Cloud interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing betwixt you and Heaven, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Aſcenſion of your Prayers: but no cloud is ſo thick as <hi>Uncharitableneſs:</hi> This darkens the whole Heaven of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Exerciſes, rendering them void of all Efficacy and Advantage, for <hi>Whatſoever you do without Charity, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth nothing;</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3.</p>
            <p>God has made of one Blood, and Redeem'd by one Ranſom, all Nations of Men, ſo that you are not to harden your Bowels againſt any that partake with you of the ſame Common Nature and Redemption. And therefore, if you want Tenderneſs of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41876:41"/>Heart, you are humbly to importune the Father of Compaſſions, to give it you, that you may be deeply affected with the Miſeries and Calamities of all Men, and imploy your Abilities for their Succour and Relief Beg the <hi>Holy Spirit of Love</hi> to dwell in your Heart, and to caſt out thence Malice, Hatred, and Uncharitableneſs, and to beget in you that <hi>Pious, Generous Temper of Mind,</hi> which ſeeks not only to pleaſe your ſelf, but alſo <hi>your Neighbour for his Good to Edification. And ſeeing that all your doings without Charity are nothing worth, beſeech God to pour into your Heart that moſt excellent Gift of Charity, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which whoſoever liveth is counted dead before him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What was it that provok'd God to animadvert ſo ſeverely upon <hi>Corah</hi> and his Accomplices, when they came to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer? Was their <hi>Incenſe</hi> unſavory? Or, were their <hi>Cenſers</hi> unhallow'd? Was their Altar profane? Or did they offer with Strange Fire? No, but the fault was in themſelves, their Hearts were Proud and Stubborn, leven'd with En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41876:42"/>and Malice, and this was what kindled Gods Wrath, and provok'd him to an unheard of <hi>Method</hi> of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>For they did not dye the common death, or as every one dieth, but the Lord made a new thing, and the earth open'd her mouth and ſwallow'd them up, and they went down quick into the pit; Numb.</hi> 16.29, 30.</q> Malice made the offering of theſe Wretches un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome, and it ſtill corrupts not only Prayer, but makes all other Solemn Acts of Religion to loſe their Acceptance with the Almighty. For he has no Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in Wickedneſs, neither can any evil dwell with him. <hi>Such as be fooliſh ſhall not ſtand in his ſight, and he hateth all them that work vanity; Pſal.</hi> 5.4, 5. Such as run eagerly upon Sin, and are as 'twere mad to commit it, ſhall periſh through their own imagination, and the Lord ſhall caſt them out in the Multitude of their Tranſgreſſions. Their own Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, Uncharitable Deſigns of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief ſhall betray them to Ruin, and their <hi>very Prayers ſhall become an Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation unto the Lord,</hi> and be no more
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41876:42"/>acceptable than was of Old the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting unto God what they had no Value for themſelves, ſuch as Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean things, or the Refuſe of their Flock.</p>
            <p>God is obliged by Promiſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper and crown your Fidelity in his Service, and to Defend, and with <hi>his Favour, to compaſs you as with a Shield.</hi> He will open his Ear to your Petitions, and hearken to the Voice of your Prayer, which you make in Faith and Charity; only have this always in Mind; <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>That as there is a great Benefit in Prayer, ſo there is ſome Difficulty to diſcharge it aright:</hi>
               </q> And that it is Impoſſible to do this without due Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paredneſs. <q rend="inline">Which being maturely conſider'd by the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, they never began their Publick Prayers, till the Prieſt had raiſed their Minds with a Preparatory Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</q> To which Pious Cuſtom our own Church had an Eye, when She Order'd him that miniſters to Prepare the Congregation for Prayers with the Reading ſome ſelect Sentences of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41876:43"/>and after that is done, with a ſhort Affectionate Exhortation. That by this means the People might be Stir'd up and Excited to a devout and reverent Deportment; and to <hi>Draw nigh unto God with their Hearts, as well as their Lips.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And from what has now been ſaid you will be eaſily able to conclude, <q rend="inline">That there is a Moral Impoſſibility your Prayers ſhould prevail, while you remain Impenitent.</q> And tho' one main Branch of your Prayer is, for the Remiſſion of your Faults, yet you cannot expect this, till you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to forſake them. To confeſs and bewail with your Tongue the Sin you approve and cheriſh in your Heart, will make all your Prayers but an Heap of Indignities againſt God, and of Imprecations upon your ſelf.</p>
            <p>When therefore you come to Adore, Worſhip and Serve the Lord, your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Thoughts and External Actions, are to be Purified from Sin by Sincere Repentance. <hi>For God heareth not the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent, nor thoſe who regard iniquity in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41876:43"/>their heart; John</hi> 9.31. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. In a Word; all the ſame Things that are requir'd of you, when you come to the Lord's Supper, are requir'd of you, when you come to Prayer: Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>To examine your ſelf whether you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent you truly of your former ſins, ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly purpoſing to lead a new life; have a lively faith in God's mercy through Chriſt, a thankful remembrance of his death, and to be in charity with all men.</hi>
               </q> And when you are thus rightly prepar'd to offer Prayers unto God, and rightly quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, he will hear in Heaven, and from thence bleſs you in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Twenty Firſt <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Trinity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GRant unto Us, we beſeech thee Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lord, (and to all thy Faithful Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) Pardon and Peace, that we may be cleanſed from all our Sins, and ſerve Thee with a quiet Mind, through Jeſus Chriſt Our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:41876:44"/>
               <head>Twenty Fourth <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Trinity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord, We beſeech Thee, abſolve us from our Offences; That through Thy bountiful Goodneſs we may all be deliver'd from the bands of thoſe Sins, which by our Frailty we have Committed. Grant this, O Heavenly Father, for Jeſus Chriſt's ſake, Our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Circumſpection at Prayer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving already given you an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of that Preparation which is requir'd when you come to Prayer, and ſhewn the Neceſſity thereof, and wherein it conſiſts: I am now to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with the <hi>Circumſpection</hi> you are to uſe at the performance of this Great and Solemn Act of Religion.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Circumſpection</hi> I underſtand your care and diligence to deep your Soul
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41876:44"/>Devout, and your Body Reverent du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of Prayer.</p>
            <p>And Firſt, as for the <hi>Circumſpection</hi> which regards the keeping of your Soul Devout, it does in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure conſiſt in avoiding as far as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, whatever may occaſion the Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of your Thoughts in Prayer; which are chiefly ſuch as now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Inconſtancy and Unſettledneſs of Mind; by reaſon whereof your Thoughts are diſtracted and divided contrary ways: an Emblem of this unhappy State of Man, with reſpect to the wandring of his Thoughts, has been ingeniouſly enough drawn out in the way of a Picture, wherein Chriſt is ſuppos'd to be hanging on the Croſs, and the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries upon their knees looking up to him, and breathing out the different aſpirings of their Souls, according to the expreſſion in the Goſpel, <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh.</hi> Out of the mouth of the one flows a Label directing itſelf in a ſtrait line to to the Wounds of a Bleeding Saviour,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41876:45"/>Praying to be made Partaker of the Merits of the Blood that he ſhed: from the Mouth of the other are ſeen to proceed ſeveral Labels waving to and fro, ſome pointing one way and ſome another; ſome to the Fields and Rural Sports, and Diverſions; others to the Sea, to Trade and Buſineſs; ſome are made up of corrupt Paſſions and Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, others are fill'd with unlawful De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires or the recital of ſinful Pleaſures paſt, and many other things of the like Nature. The firſt Man would not ſuffer any thing to interrupt or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him in the Prayers he offer'd, but like a Beam of Light they ſwiftly, and directly made their way to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Object; the other did not mind what he was about, but gave his thoughts the Reins, and left them at liberty to ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble where they liſt. And though he may ſeem to look the ſame way as the other did, yet his mind is roving all the while, verifying the expreſſion of the Prophet (quoted by our Saviour; <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.8.) ſuch a one may ſeem to draw nigh with his mouth and honour God
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41876:45"/>with his lips, but his heart is far from him.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Carking immoderate Worldly Thoughts are the next thing which diſcompoſe your Mind, and beget in you diffidence and diſtruſt in God, on whom you ought to caſt all your Cares, as being <hi>well aſſur'd that he careth for you.</hi> And this, I conceive, was meant by S. <hi>Paul</hi> when he exhorted the <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians,</hi> that in their Devotions they ſhould <hi>be careful for nothing, but in every thing by prayer and ſupplications, with thanksgiving, to make their requeſts known unto God; Phil.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p>The Soul of it ſelf is nimble and active, and in an inſtant can mount up to Heaven in Prayer, which is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore call'd an <hi>Elevation of the Soul; Pſal.</hi> 25.1. But Earthly-mindedneſs keeps it fluttering below, and faſtens its Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to the Duſt, which does ſo clog them, that they cannot aſpire to the things above. You are therefore to take off the Weights which the World hangs upon your Thoughts, and which diſtract them in your Supplications.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41876:46"/>For whilſt you cheriſh immoderate De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the World, they will either hinder you from Praying at all, or from Praying as you ought.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Idleneſs and Sloth may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other occaſion of the wandring of your Thoughts in Prayer. For perhaps you will not take pains to ſuppreſs and correct the Extravagances of your Thoughts, and to keep them within due Bounds and Meaſures. By which neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect your Soul becomes <hi>like the field of the ſlothful, and the vineyard of the man void of underſtanding, which was all grown over with thorns, and nettles had covered the face thereof, and the ſtone-wall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was broken down.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to whatever occaſion the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of your Thoughts in Prayer may be imputed, it highly concerns you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly to avoid them. And in a great meaſure you may be able to do this, if you uſe that due atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and zeal in Prayer, which you muſt own to be wholly requiſit and needful.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:41876:46"/>
            <p>And firſt, you muſt uſe all due At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; for by it you fix your Thoughts upon God, and frame to your ſelf a ſtrong and lively <hi>Idea</hi> of his Preſence, and poſſeſs your heart with awful appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of his Majeſty: Ever having in mind that your Prayer is to him, <hi>in whom you live, move, and have your being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>Jews</hi> enter the Synagogue, they for a while ſtand ſilently in the poſture of Prayer, before they begin it; in which time they labour to affect their minds with his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Attributes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Buxtorf. Syn. Jud. l.</hi> 5.</note> whom they are come to Worſhip; that the Conſideration thereof may help the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to keep them from being vain and trifling. And one of their Maſters taught his Scholars that before they began their Prayers, <q rend="inline">They ſhould think a while on him to whom they make them.</q> And it would doubtleſs much contribute to the reſtraint and amendment of that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring in Prayer, to which you will find your ſelf wonderfully prone, to conſider in whoſe Preſence you are, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite diſproportion that there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41876:47"/>God and you. For you can no ſooner conſider that it is God to whom you ſpeak in Prayer, but the Thought thereof will quicken your Attention, and render you apprehenſive, and make you in a dread and ſurprize, if you find your ſelf heedleſs and unconcern'd in ſo <hi>Important</hi> a <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> and in ſo <hi>Great</hi> a <hi>Preſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Attention is a proper cure for wandring in Prayer, becauſe it keeps your Mind and Thoughts to every ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and word thereof. For that At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention which is to accompany Prayer, is a ſettled and compoſed Temper of Mind, which gathers all your Thoughts together, and fixes them upon the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Buſineſs you are about.</p>
            <p>And tho' Idle, Impertinent, Wandring Thoughts, will be ever ready to thruſt themſelves upon you, and intrude into your Holy Offices, ſo that you cannot be always totally free from them, yet by Attention you may much hinder and keep them from making any ſtay, or getting the Dominion over you ſo far as to corrupt or captivate the Will. So
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41876:47"/>that, notwithſtanding that this Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, to which you are liable, may be your Unhappineſs, yet it can never be your Sin, as long as you ſtrive againſt it, and deny it your Approbation and Conſent. And tho' you can never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely conquer this Wandring of your Thoughts in Prayer, yet you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain and deal with it as <hi>Abraham</hi> with the ravenous Birds, which he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>Drove away, when they came to devour his Sacrifice; Gen.</hi> 15.11,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cauſinus,</hi> (who was no contemptible Director of Devotion) adviſes his Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant to ſtay upon every Sentence in Vocal Prayer, the ſpace of a breathing, and in that time to ponder the Words he pronounces, and to conſider the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to whom he ſpeaks, and his own Unworthineſs. He would likewiſe have him ſo to apply the Prayer, as if it had been made for his own particular uſe; and to eſpouſe all the Affections which the Compoſer of the Prayer had when the Holy Ghoſt moved him to compoſe it, and aſſiſted him in the Compoſition.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:41876:48"/>
            <p>But your want of Attention will hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you from the obſervation of this advice, and will alſo hinder God from regarding your Prayers. For can you expect God ſhould attend to the Prayers, to which you do not attend your ſelf? Can you hope that he with a Paternal kindneſs and affection ſhould open his Ears to thoſe, who are not ſerious before him? If at the ſame time you call to Heaven, your Thoughts are ſo ſet upon Earthly concerns, ſo that when you have done Praying, you ſcarce know what you have been do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; is not this <hi>to offer the ſacrifice of Fools? Who are raſh with their mouth and haſty in their heart to utter any thing before God; not conſidering that he is in the heavens, and they on the earth: Eccleſ.</hi> 5.2. You are not then to run over your Prayers <hi>by Rote,</hi> but with recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected Thoughts to Weigh, and be At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive to what you ſay unto him, with whom is Terrible Majeſty, and who is a conſuming Fire.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, 'Twould not a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to your exerciſe of Attention,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41876:48"/>in Prayer, if you would conſider that the <hi>Perfection</hi> of your Prayers is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the degrees of your <hi>Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and that the more Attentive you are in Prayer, the greater benefit you receive by it. And here one way to mend your Attention, is, to repeat the Prayer again wherein you have found it defective, and to continue this courſe till you find your heedleſneſs worn off and removed. For by this means you will defeat the Devil, who occaſions your unattentiveneſs by injecting wicked Thoughts into your mind, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting you with amuſing objects. But it would be Satans intereſt to give over tempting you thus to Wander in Prayer, if once he finds your ſenſe of it arming you againſt ſuch Wandring, and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your Attention, and rendring you more circumſpect.</p>
            <p>Now, this <hi>Repetition</hi> comes not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſs of that which our Lord cenſur'd for vain and idle. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.7. For in this caſe you do not repeat your Prayers over and over, out of a conceit that God will the ſooner be
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41876:49"/>mov'd to hear you; or that by your Repetition he better underſtands your meaning (which was the Opinion of thoſe Heathens, whoſe Repetition of their Prayers was condemn'd by our Saviour:) but the Repetition now ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of is to mend your Incogitancy, and Thoughtleſneſs of the Buſineſs you are about. For it is not the tumbling out of ſo many words, or of the ſame words over and over again, or the Length and Multitude of them, that is pleaſing unto God, any farther than as they expreſs the fervency of your Spirit, the Importunity of your Zeal, and the greatneſs of your Wants. But if you affect Length and Repetition in Prayer, either out of Hypocriſie or Vainglory, it will be ſo far from pleaſing God, and prevailing with him, that it will have a quite contrary effect. And this you may conclude from our Saviours car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in this Particular, who diſliking the Heathens Length and Vociferation in Prayer, gave his Diſciples a ſhort, comprehenſive Form, which they were to uſe and imitate in their calling upon God.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:41876:49"/>
            <p>Fourthly, When you find out the Wandring of your Thoughts, and that you are ready to mind any thing rather than that you ſhould, there is no ſuch Cure for this as Attention. For by it you inſtantly recal your ſelf to your Buſineſs, and to a ſerious min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of what you are about. And you will ſoon perceive your obligation to do this, when you conſider that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing it, you ſlight one of the moſt Eminent Parts of God's Worſhip, <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>By drawing nigh unto him with your lips, when your heart is far from him.</hi>
               </q> Beſides, if you exactly weigh your lack of Attention, you will find it has in it a great degree of Atheiſm. For not to Attend to what you ſay, when you ſpeak unto God, betrays in you a low eſteem of his Majeſty, and that you have mean, unworthy Thoughts of the Godhead; which has ever been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a piece of the vileſt Atheiſm. Call home then your roving Thoughts, and employ them in what you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. Get as near Heaven as you can, and have your mind there, and there
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:41876:50"/>only. For unleſs this be your care and practice when you offer to God the Sacrifice of Prayer, you will be but like the Cheat in <hi>Plutarch;</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Who brought unto the Altar of his Idol the Skeleton of an Ox cover'd with a fair hide, pretending that he offer'd a goodly Sacrifice of Fleſh and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails, when indeed there was nothing but a skin full of bones.</q> You would count him a vain Thoughtleſs Perſon, worthy of Ridicule and Contempt, who coming to beg his Life of his Prince, ſhould give over his Suit to run after a Butterfly. And yet this is your fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, when in Prayer you ſuffer your mind to be carried away to imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent objects, and faſten your Thoughts to the things which you ought to avoid thinking on. Can you hope (as was but now intimated) God ſhould incline <hi>His</hi> ears to the Prayers, to which you will not incline your own? That he ſhould regard your Petitions, when you do not regard them your ſelf? You may eaſily obſerve your aptneſs to heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs at Devotion; and how many
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:41876:50"/>things, all foreign to what you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, do interpoſe when you fall down upon your Knees; you may find to your ſorrow, the Common Enemy tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering with your Heart, at the ſame time your tongue is ſpeaking unto God. 'Tis therefore neceſſary to recollect your ſelf, to fix your mind when you come before the Almighty, and to affect your Soul with this conſideration; <q rend="inline">That you are not ſure of another op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to ſolicit him with your Prayers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But if through the frailty of humane Nature you cannot always exerciſe that Attention, which is neceſſary to reſtrain your wandring in Prayer; then beg of God to aſſiſt your frailty, and to eſtabliſh your Attention againſt all avocations. And (tho' they may ſteal upon you at Devotion) that he would enable you by his Grace to reject them. And if after all you cannot be rid thereof, be ſure to give them no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, but to deny them your approbation and conſent. For when you do ſincerely ſtrive againſt them,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41876:51"/>God will either crown your endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with conqueſt over them, or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them if they prove invincible. But if the want of attention in Prayer be the fruit of your own wilful Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, you can hope neither for God's aſſiſtance nor his pardon, whilſt this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence is continued.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Zeal in Prayer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ZEal is another help againſt the wandring of your thoughts in Prayer. Now Zeal is a ſacred warmth and fervour of Mind, and an affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate earneſtneſs to have your Prayers heard. For it is not enough that you keep your Thoughts to what is utter'd by him that miniſtreth in the publick Service, and to ponder and mind every word he ſpeaks, but you muſt do it with intention and fervency. For both all wandring, and all deadneſs in Prayer muſt be driven away. True Zeal will
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41876:51"/>melt and diſſolve your heart, and make you cry unto God with the utmoſt ſtrength of Spirit: and it will move you to be wholly bent to obtain what you crave. A cold indifferent Suitor ſeldom prevails with Men. For if a begger ſhould ask relief at your hands, and do it in ſo looſe a manner, as that he ſeem'd indifferent whether he had it or no, you would think he had either little Want, or great Pride; and ſo have no heart to relieve him. Now, the things you beg of God are ſo much above the rate of any ordinary Alms, that you can never expect they ſhould be given you, if you are ſlight and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy in asking them. When you appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, and fully conſider, the matter of your Prayer, and add to it a devout earneſtneſs of deſire, then may your Devotion be truly ſaid to be Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. And tho' this quality chiefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides in the Soul, yet it often appears in the geſtures of the Body. As was ſeen in <hi>Moſes;</hi> who when he made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Fell down before the Lord, forty days, and forty nights,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41876:52"/>and did neither eat bread nor drink water, becauſe of all the ſins that</hi> Iſrael <hi>had ſin'd, in doing wickedly in the ſight of the Lord to provoke him to anger. Deut.</hi> 9.18.</q> And the Zeal of this meekeſt of Men, was more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, when he deſir'd God <hi>rather to blot him out of his BOOK,</hi> than that he ſhould execute his menaces againſt <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael. Elias</hi> caſt himſelf upon the earth to expreſs his Earneſtneſs in praying for Rain. And the ever Bleſſed Jeſus <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued all night in Prayer, and offer'd up his ſupplications with ſtrong crying and tears; Luke</hi> 6.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7. And pray'd with ſuch Ardour and Affectionateneſs, that <hi>the ſweat fell from him to the ground, as if it had been great drops of blood; Luke</hi> 22.44. And this zeal and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs ſeems to have been meant by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he exhorted <hi>Believers to be inſtant in Prayer: Rom.</hi> 12.12. <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>To ſtrive in prayer: Rom.</hi> 15.30.</q> 
               <hi>To la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour frequently in prayer: Col.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Night and day to pray exceedingly: To pray al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with all prayer: praying earneſtly.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:41876:52"/>
               <hi>Jam.</hi> 6.7. By all which ſacred Texts, that Zeal and Vehemency ſeems to be enjoyn'd, which I now recommend as an excellent help againſt the wandring of your thoughts in Prayer.</p>
            <p>Which is a fault whereof you can not be guilty, when you pray with ſpiritual Affection, with ardent Deſire, with a fervent Mind, and with a Heart inflam'd with that Zeal which the Holy Ghoſt kindles in it. God regards not the Prayers which you offer, when you do not ſtir up your Affections, and chafe your deſires, and move your mind into a warmth. The Great Ruler of the world will not liſten to cold, luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm Devotions. Such Prayers can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reach Heaven which want Zeal and Love, the only Wings that ſhould carry them thither.</p>
            <p>Be careful then when you approach God, to raiſe up your Soul to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pitch of Zeal and Earneſtneſs that you are able: And becauſe that of your ſelf you are not able to do this, beſeech the Divine Omnipotence to inflame your Heart with the heavenly fire of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:41876:53"/>and when it is obtain'd, beware of quenching it with wilful ſin, or let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it go out again for want of fuel, or ſtirring up and imploying it.</p>
            <p>And there want no Motives to beget in you this Fervency in Prayer, when you conſider God's wonderful kindneſs, and carry the thoughts thereof through your whole Devotion. For, to think that he is not only good by Nature, but alſo in communicating his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits: That he is ready upon your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to blot out your tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and to be merciful to your Sins. Such Thoughts as theſe are good inward motives to raiſe your heart into Zeal, <hi>When you lift up your voice, and call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord, either in his houſe, or your own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Firſt, when you come to the Lord's houſe, to joyn in publick Prayers, you have a good opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to ſhew your Earneſtneſs and Zeal. God has Promis'd a ſpecial bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the joynt Requeſts which the Faithful make in his <hi>Houſe,</hi> and that He will be in the midſt of them, and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:41876:53"/>beſtow his Mercies, and ſet marks of Favour on them, when they meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>in the unity of the ſpirit, and in the bond of peace.</hi> And your abſence from the Publick Prayers cannot be excus'd without an important occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; for if it be wilful and deliberate, you cut your ſelf off from the Church and from the partaking of thoſe Prayers, wherein all are in common concern'd. And by this means you inflict a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon your ſelf (even a ſort of Excommunication) which is never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted by the Church, but in caſe of the moſt heinous offences.</p>
            <p>The ſame Zeal and Attention are alſo requiſite in the Prayers made in your Family, which are a ſort of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayers,</hi> becauſe all the Members of the Houſhold joyn therein. And it belongs to the Maſter of the Family carefully to provide for this office; and to ſee nothing be wanting for the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of their Souls, who are under his Government. For the Family is Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh where God is not worſhipt; and where the Maſter does not reſolve
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:41876:54"/>with <hi>Joſhua, That he, and his houſe will ſerve the Lord. Joſh.</hi> 24.15.</p>
            <p>And as to the Prayers you make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, when you are <hi>ſolus cum ſolo,</hi> and have no witneſs of what you do, but only God and your Conſcience; yet becauſe that even here you are ſubject to Wandring and Diſtraction, as well, as you are in company, you have need of the ſame Zeal and Attention to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect it.</p>
            <p>In your private Devotions you may be more particular, according to your perſonal Neceſſities, and you may uſe therein a greater freedom both in words and geſtures, than you can in publick. But ſtill the Devotion of the Heart is therein requir'd, as being that which God principally regards. And as it is your duty to perform all theſe ſorts of Prayers, ſo it is likewiſe your duty to be Zealous and Attentive at them all. Prayer in your Family and Cloſet, will not excuſe your Prayer at Church; all are requir'd, all are neceſſary, and one muſt not be taken in exchange for the other, <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>And whoſoever is diligent
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:41876:54"/>in publick Prayer, and yet negligent in private, it is to be fear'd he rather ſeeks to approve himſelf to men than to God.</hi>
               </q> Which is contrary to the mind of our Saviour, who commands you to Pray to God in ſecret; and from him alone to expect your Reward, and not from the vain praiſes of Men. You have been often told <hi>That Prayer is that part of divine worſhip, which the Soul is to pay unto the Lord;</hi> and <hi>you have</hi> alſo been told, with what Circumſpection it ought to be perform'd. Give me leave to conclude this particular with obſerving, that tho' Prayer be a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual duty, and the proper buſineſs of the Soul, yet the Body has its ſhare and part therein. For both being God's workmanſhip and purchaſe, both ought to give him homage and obſervance. Now, the obſervance the Body ought to pay unto God in Prayer, conſiſts in ſuch lowly, decent, and reverent ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, as may teſtify the humility and reverence of the Soul. Bowing, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and the like external acts of Religious Worſhip, are a particular right
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:41876:55"/>belonging to God; before whom you are <hi>to fall down and kneel, for he is your maker, your ſhepherd, your protector.</hi> The Royal Author of the 95. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> does affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately call upon every one joyntly to adore, worſhip, and pray unto God; and to make the members of the Body, the partners and witneſſes of the real devotion of the Heart, and to joyn inward and outward reverence together: That the ſubmiſſive and lowly geſtures of the Body may ſerve to expreſs and ſignifie the ſincere humility of the Soul. For tho' the humbleſt external bodily geſtures are the leaſt conſiderable thing in Prayer, as having little or no propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the neceſſary diſpoſitions of the Soul; yet they are of ſuch moment, that if you pray, without them, it looks as if you did not conſider or know what a weighty buſineſs you are about, nor had a ſenſe of God's Dignity, or of your own Vileneſs. But in theſe bodily Geſtures you are carefully to avoid whatſoever is vain, fantaſtical, and ſuperſtitious; and to keep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bounds of decency and prudence.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:41876:55"/>And your geſtures being thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted, they will help to heighten in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Devotion in your ſelf, and be an happy means to raiſe the Devotion of others. But I leave the farther pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of this particular, to conſider of the Frequency you ought to uſe in Prayer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of Frequency in Prayer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THough Prayer be a Duty, which you are never to neglect, yet there is not any Text in Scripture that determines how often you are to uſe it. The Inſpired Word poſitively com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands you to call upon God, but it has left it to your Conſcience how fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently you are to do it. The Scripture that is moſt peremptory in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, is, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17. where <hi>S. Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts to <hi>Pray without ceaſing.</hi> By which Text you are certainly obliged to theſe two things, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:41876:56"/>
            <p n="1">1. Not to grow reſtive in Prayer, but therein to be conſtant and perſevering, it being an homage you are to pay continually to God, and that without which you can never hope to be ſafe and proſperous. For Praying gives you a title to God's ſafeguard and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and it muſt be as laſting as your own wants, and obligation to worſhip God. And therefore till you find you have no need of God's Mercies, nor any tye upon you to adore him, you muſt <hi>Pray without ceaſing.</hi> Which words imply,</p>
            <p>Secondly, That your Prayers under the Goſpel, muſt bear proportion with the <hi>Daily Sacrifices</hi> under the Law, which were conſtantly offer'd Morning and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening. And you cannot ſink your Prayers to a leſſer proportion, or pray ſeldomer than Morning and Evening. It being highly reaſonable and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that you ſhould begin all your works with calling upon God for his direction and bleſſing; and end them with praiſe and thanks for his protection and aſſiſtance.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:41876:56"/>
            <p>Some have interpreted the Apoſtles words <hi>(Pray without ceaſing,)</hi> of ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding every moment of their life in Prayer; which can be no error, if it be underſtood of ſuch an excellent frame of Spirit, and pious diſpoſition of Mind, as is alway in readineſs to call upon God. This religious temper and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitual devoutneſs of Soul, is like the Holy fire of the Sanctuary, which never went out: For it is always ready to flame in pious ejaculations and affectionate breathings after God. And when for want of meet circumſtances your Prayers cannot be Vocal, yet they may be Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. And in this ſenſe you may be ſaid to pray <hi>without ceaſing,</hi> which according to <hi>Diodati,</hi> is to be underſtood rather of <hi>the heart and affection,</hi> than of the <hi>tongue and words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho' you have not always leiſure and opportunity to be upon your knees, yet you never want either to bow your heart before God, and by a pious temper of mind, and ſpirit of Devotion, to lift it up to the Lord. And notwithſtanding the Scripture has left the frequency of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41876:57"/>Prayer undetermined, yet you may take your meaſures as to publick Prayers, from the Rules of the Church; and in your private Devotions from the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Holy Men.</p>
            <p>And firſt, the Rules of the Church acquaint you with the ſtated times of Publick Prayer, from which you are not to be abſent, when you can poſſibly be at them. And it muſt be a matter of conſiderable moment that can juſtify your abſence from the Lords Houſe at the ſet times of Prayer. Now according to ſome Expoſitors you may be ſaid to <hi>Pray without ceaſing,</hi> when you obſerve the <hi>hours</hi> or <hi>times</hi> of <hi>Prayer,</hi> appointed by the Church But if you were not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd to obſerve ſuch <hi>ſtated times of Prayer,</hi> yet the very <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Piety,</hi> would oblige you to obſerve them. For both theſe teach you to omit no occaſion to expreſs your Duty to God: <q rend="inline">Which conſiſts in <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping him, giving him thanks, calling upon him, honouring his holy Name and his word, and ſerving him truly all the days of our life.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:41876:57"/>
            <p>And as to Frequency in your Private Devotion, you have the Examples of Holy men in Scripture for your Guide. And firſt of <hi>David, Who, evening, morning and at noon, did cry unto the Lord and he heard his voice; Pſal.</hi> 55.17. With his conſtant importunity he re-inforc'd an impreſſion of his Prayers upon God, the better to move him to grant them. <hi>My voice ſhalt thou hear in the morning, O Lord, in the morning will I direct my prayer unto thee, and will look up; Pſal.</hi> 5.3. This religious Prince made the firſt fruits, and prime of the day to preſent his ſupplications before God; and after the manner of earneſt Petitioners he fix'd his eyes on heaven, reſolving to wait and never to move, till the Lord hearken'd unto the voice of his Prayer; nay, from thrice, <hi>David</hi> encreas'd his praying to <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times a day, Pſal.</hi> 119.164. rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding, that he could never ſufficiently admire and magnifie the Divine Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies; and that if he had had nothing elſe to be the matter of his praiſes, yet he thought himſelf bound continually to extol them. It's true, the phraſe <hi>(ſeven times)</hi>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:41876:58"/>may be taken in a larger ſenſe, and not meerly to ſignifie that number, but be look'd upon as a <hi>mode</hi> of <hi>ſpeech,</hi> denoting a great frequency in Prayer, and ſhewing that <hi>David</hi> was daily very often imploy'd therein; which cuſtom to pray often was not peculiar to <hi>David</hi> only, but was alſo uſed by God's peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple many hundred years after he ſaw cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. As was ſeen in <hi>Daniel,</hi> who when he knew the Dead-warrant was ſign'd for his execution, <hi>Went into his houſe, and his windows being open in his chamber towards Jeruſalem, he kneel'd upon his knees three times a day, and prayed and gave thanks before his God, as he did afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time; Dan.</hi> 6.10. The laſt words ſhew, that it was not an emergent zeal, or an extraordinary fit of Devotion, but that it was his conſtant and uſual pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, to pray thrice a day, which was the common cuſtom of the <hi>Jews;</hi> who made <hi>Morning, noon, and evening the three times of prayer; Acts</hi> 3.1. and 10.4. and 9.31. which cuſtom was obſerv'd alſo by the Apoſtles, and ſome Devouter Chriſtians went farther, and pray'd ſix
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:41876:58"/>times a day, taking in the <hi>Compline,</hi> or the Prayer made by good men at nine at night.</p>
            <p>But if you ſhould imagine theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to be imitable, and that it would exhauſt too much of your time to be ſo often on your knees; then revolve with your ſelf;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That you are never ſo far to immerſe and bury your ſelf in worldly buſineſs, as not to allow ſpace to begin and end the day with Prayer. And you cannot juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly complain you want time to be thus of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Devotion, when you conſider how much time you can find to caſt away, if not upon that which is <hi>vicious,</hi> yet upon that which is wholly <hi>impertinent</hi> to your Station. If you would prudently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench your Recreations, and imploy in <hi>Piety</hi> the hours you ſpend in <hi>Vanities,</hi> you would never be ſtraitned for time to beſtow in Devotion. The true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of your having ſo <hi>little</hi> time to give to this is, becauſe you laviſh ſo much away in things of ſo little moment, if not worſe, that when it is paſt you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but condemn your ſelf for it.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:41876:59"/>
            <p>But ſeeing you muſt one day give an account of the ſpending of your time, it behoves you to be wary how you ſpend it. And the more time you have waſtfully miſpent already, the more ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally careful you ought to be of that which yet remains. And to redeem the hours you have thrown away upon Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties, by a vertuous and religious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of thoſe God ſhall yet pleaſe to vouchſafe you.</p>
            <p>Conſider, Secondly, how reaſonable and juſt a thing it is, that you allow a liberal portion of your time to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, who is graciouſly pleas'd to allow ſo much to your own. God does not grudge you ſpace enough for your law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Buſineſs, and neceſſary Diverſions; but then he expects you would not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach upon thoſe minutes which are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to Religious Exerciſes. It is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obſervable, That men of Higheſt Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Weightieſt Imployments, have been the moſt frequent and diligent in their Devotions. And of this truth you have two known, famous examples of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> the one a King, the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:41876:59"/>other a prime Miniſter of State, yet the one prays ſeven, and the other three times a day.</p>
            <p>Conſider, thirdly, how diſingenuous and unthankful it would be in you, to repine at the allowance of a ſmall parcel of your time to the ſervice of the Great Maſter of Heaven and Earth; if you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it to be juſt and reaſonable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſo many hours ſervice every day from thoſe that ſtand in the ſame relation to your ſelf. But as to the parcels of time you are to allow to private Devotion, they muſt be proportion'd to the nature of your Station and neceſſary Buſineſs; and to be no more, or longer, than will conſiſt with your urgent Affairs and be no prejudice to them. And that you have time enough to do this, without hindering the due diſcharge of the Duties of your calling, or even your neceſſary, honeſt Diverſions, will be evident, if you conſider, the nature of Devotion in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and in particular, wherein the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate conſiſts.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:41876:60"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of the Nature of Devotion,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>AND Firſt, as to the nature of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in general, it is ſuch an exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Soul, as may for the greateſt part be tranſacted without interrupting the actions of the Body. So that you need not always cloſet your ſelf, and lay aſide your honeſt Affairs, to be Devout.</p>
            <p>Devotion is the entertaining of pious, uſeful and wiſe Thoughts in your Mind: it puts you upon weighing every thing you do, and reflecting on whatever you have done amiſs. It moves you to look forward to the temptation that approaches you, and puts you upon arming your ſelf againſt it with ſerious thoughts of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Hell. And when your Mind is really devout, it moves you to look up to the former with earneſt <hi>deſires</hi> and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to <hi>gain</hi> it, and down to the latter, with inceſſant <hi>care</hi> to <hi>eſcape</hi> it.</p>
            <p>Now, you may do all this in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt throng of your worldly Concernments.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:41876:60"/>For Devotion is an act of the Soul, whoſe motions are ſo nimble and ſprightly, that they have but little dependence on the Body: which latter can ſcarce be ever ſo taken up, as to keep the former from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing devout. For what bodily Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can hinder you from lifting up your heart, <hi>even lifting it up unto the Lord?</hi> what Buſineſs can reſtrain your Soul from ſending up its affectionate Ejaculations, holy Wiſhes, and devout Vows unto God? If you have an implicit deſire upon all opportunities to advance the Glory of God, if you Eat, and Drink, and Sleep and recreate your ſelf moderately to this end, to enable you to ſerve God the better, and ſo incorporate, and interweave ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Thoughts and Ejaculations, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your Natural, Moral, and Civil Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments (ſo they be lawful and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and not ſordid and ſervile) you make your common actions to become works of Piety, and exerciſes of Religion. What office of your Calling can keep you from conſidering every morning the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations to which that day you may be liable, and how you may beſt ſtrengthen
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:41876:61"/>and fore-arm your ſelf againſt them? What buſineſs can be ſo urgent and haſty, as not to give you time every morning to recommend your ſelf to God, in ſome ſhort, devout and zealous Prayer?</p>
            <p>And what great pains or time will it coſt you, to take every evening an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your Actions of the paſt day, and with humble importunity to beg God to pardon ſuch as have been evil, and to render him thanks that he has enabled you to do any that are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; and that he has deliver'd you from any evil of Sin or Danger? And having thus begun and concluded the day, you may comfortably commit your ſelf to God's Mercy and Protection; whoſe only guard is abundantly ſufficient to keep you ſecure: And then cloſe your meditations with that of the Pſalmiſt, <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>I will lay me down in peace, and ſleep, for thou Lord only makeſt me dwell in ſafety.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And this plain conſtant courſe of private Devotion, is that which was enjoyn'd by our Bleſſed Lord, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. when he bad you go to your Cloſet, and there to ſhut the doors after you. And there is
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:41876:61"/>at leaſt a great convenience, if not a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, of doing thus: Firſt, becauſe you may have many Sins to beg pardon for, and many particular Mercies to implore, and many Wants to be ſupply'd, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Graces to be obtain'd, which are not ſo fit for you to pray for in Publick. And therefore you are to go to him who is in Secret, and to whom you may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſom your ſelf without fear of Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or Reproach.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This conſtant, daily courſe of Private Devotion, will beget in your mind both an Awe, and Affection to God, and alſo make you in love with this Duty, becauſe it brings you to a familiarity with him. Beſides this Cuſtom in Private De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion will wear off all the ſurmiſed dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties thereof, and make it become eaſie and pleaſant. And when it is duly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged you will find it ſo far from interfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring either with your lawful Imployment, or your neceſſary Recreation; that it will pleaſantly mingle and aſſociate with both.</p>
            <p>You read how the unjuſt Judge, in the Parable, granted the Widow's Suit, not out of love to Juſtice, but for his own
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:41876:62"/>Eaſe, <hi>Leſt by her continual coming ſhe ſhould weary him; Luke</hi> 18.5. The deſign of the Parable, is firſt to inſtruct frequency and perſeverance in Prayer, and that therein you are neither to be negligent nor tyr'd. Next, it ſhews the efficacy and force of conſtant Devotion, and importunate Prayer, and how mightily therewith God is wrought upon; and another illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof you have in the Man that went to borrow Bread of his Neighbour. Tho' his Neighbour had lock't his doors, and himſelf and all his Family were gone to bed, and when the reſpect of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip would not work upon him, yet the Borrower ſhewing his real Want by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at that time of night, his confidence in the Man to whom he came, prevailed with him to riſe, and to lend him as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Loaves as he needed. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>But you have not only Parables, but Inſtances of the power that perſevering importunate Prayer has with the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. For <hi>Moſes</hi> by it ſo far prevailed as to put a ſort of force upon God, a kind of neceſſity of ſparing <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they had provok'd him to deſtroy them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:41876:62"/>And by it alſo <hi>Jacob</hi> wreſtled with God ſo long till he got the better, and came off with a new name, which declar'd him Victor. For God ſaid unto him, <hi>Thy name ſhall be called no more Jacob, but Iſrael: for as a Prince haſt thou power with God and men, and haſt prevailed, Gen.</hi> 32.28.</p>
            <p>And both theſe Parables and Examples recommend to your practice, earneſtneſs and perſeverance in Prayer. Wherein you need not fear being too inſtant and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, eſpecially in thoſe ſupplications which you make to God for a vertuous and holy life, while you live here, and for an happy and glorious Immortality when you go hence. For theſe are the things for which you may pray abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and which God will certainly grant through Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous. <hi>To whom,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALmighty and everlaſting God, who doſt Govern all things in Heaven and Earth; Mercifully hear the Supplications of thy People, and grant us thy Peace all the days of our Life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:41876:63"/>
            <p>
               <hi>GRant to us, Lord, we beſeech thee, the Spirit to think and do always ſuch things as be rightful; that we who cannot do any thing that is good without Thee may by Thee be enabled to live according to Thy Will, through Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>The Things to be Pray'd for.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Am now come to the laſt Thing I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, to preſent you with, <hi>viz.</hi> an Account of the Matter of Prayer, or the Things you are to beg of God; which are only ſuch as he has in his Word pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to give: and which for ſubſtance are all compris'd in the Sacred Form, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically ſtil'd <hi>The Lord's Prayer.</hi> Now, this Prayer is of like uſe with the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, and is to be the Rule of your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as that is of your Actions. And as you need do no more than what is ſet down in the Decalogue, ſo you need deſire no more than what is contain'd
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:41876:63"/>in the Lord's Prayer. To the Heads of which all your Prayers are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd, and you are to uſe in them the like Simplicity and ſober Brevity, that is us'd in this.</p>
            <p>And both the Decalogue and Lord's Prayer are of the ſame extent, both teaching you your Duty to God, your Neighbour, and your Self. The Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue teaches you what you are to do, to each of theſe, and the Lord's Prayer teaches you how you may beg of God to do them as you ought. And as the <hi>Ten Commandments</hi> were twice given by God the Father, ſo was the <hi>Lord's Prayer</hi> twice given by God the Son: once at the requeſt of his Diſciples. <hi>S. Luke</hi> 11.1, 2. and a Second time of his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, S. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.9. And when our Lord gave this Prayer he intended it to be the true Sum of all Chriſtian Prayers; and that none were to ask any thing of God but what was therein compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended.</p>
            <p>For (1.) There is not any thing that you need deſire, reſpecting your Duty to God, which is not with wonderful plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:41876:64"/>(conſidering the brevity) ſumm'd up in the three firſt Petitions of this Prayer. The firſt whereof regards your glorifying of God's Name; The ſecond the eſtabliſhing of his Authority and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, in your heart; and the laſt, your Submiſſion and Obedience to his Will. Which compriſe all that you need deſire of God in order to the right per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of your Duty towards him.</p>
            <p>And in the firſt place it teaches you to pray for the hallowing and glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God's Name. By his <hi>Name</hi> you are to underſtand in General God Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and in particular his Glorious Titles and Perfections, together with every thing that has a peculiar relation to him; as his <hi>Word,</hi> his <hi>Day,</hi> his <hi>Houſe,</hi> &amp;c. For as you owe to all theſe an aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, humble Reverence and Devotion, ſo you are to beg of God to ſtir up your heart, and to aſſiſt you to pay it as you ſhould. That he would inable you ſo to carry your ſelf toward all Things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to his <hi>Being</hi> and <hi>Service,</hi> as that all may ſee you ſincerely Honour and Worſhip his Adorable <hi>Eſſence</hi> and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies:
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:41876:64"/>For ſeeing God, who is the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Holineſs, has been pleas'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal himſelf as it were by a proper Name, and to take unto him the endearing Title of <hi>Father,</hi> honouring all Believers with the relation of his Children; it is your Duty to beg, that he would give you Grace, to Glorifie him both in Word and Deed, and that you may be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of cauſing him to be Honor'd by all men; and that neither by you, nor by your means, his Sacred Name may at any time be profan'd.</p>
            <p>And this Hallowing of God's Name is the firſt thing you are taught to pray for, and the foundation of all the reſt. For unleſs you Glorifie God, and Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie him above all Things; unleſs you acknowledge his Supreme Majeſty, and Superlative Goodneſs; you are not fit to Pray for the coming of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Which Kingdom is threefold, <hi>viz.</hi> one of Power, whereby he ruleth over all Creatures: another of Grace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ruleth in the hearts of Believers, by his Word and Spirit: and a third of Glory, which in a more Eminent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:41876:65"/>ſhall begin at the laſt Judgment: when Chriſt as man, ſhall deliver up the Kingdom to God the Father; and when all the Saints ſhall be taken in to Reign with him. And the coming of all theſe Kingdoms makes up the Second requeſt of the Lord's Prayer; for therein you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that God would exerciſe his Power in ſubduing, and his Juſtice in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Enemies; that by this means the World may be freed from that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety and Confuſion, wherewith it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds; and that every one may ſay, <hi>Verily there is a God that judgeth in the Earth: Pſal.</hi> 58.11. and plainly diſcern that this World is not govern'd by Chance, but adminiſtred and manag'd by an Almighty, All-wiſe, and moſt Juſt Providence. And as it is your Intereſt and Happineſs, ſo it ought to be your Prayer, that God's Kingdom may be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and his Authority exerciſed, to the end, that his Faithful Servants may be ſafe from their Adverſaries, and have their Neceſſities reliev'd, and their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires accompliſh'd.</p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:41876:65"/>
            <p>Next, you are to pray for the coming of God's <hi>Kingdom of Grace;</hi> that he would mercifully eſtabliſh his Throne and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion in yours and in the hearts of all men; That the Goſpel may be Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally Embrac'd; and that they who are now ſlaves to Satan, and their own vile affections, may be converted, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Devil, and profeſs themſelves Subjects of Jeſus; doing his Works, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving his Precepts and paying him Tribute, Homage and Subjection, as their Liege Lord. And whereas you daily ſee that God's Laws are broken, his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers deſpiſed, his Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments neglected, and every thing belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Solemn Worſhip ſet at nought by ſome, and ridicul'd by others; you are in Charity oblig'd to pray for a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter face of Affairs, <q rend="inline">And that he who is the giver of all Goodneſs would ſend his Grace unto you and to all People, that you may Worſhip him, Serve him and Obey him, as you ought to do.</q> And that your unruly Paſſions may be tam'd, your rebellious Luſts mortified, your naughty Deſires extinguiſh't, and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:41876:66"/>every oppoſing Thought ſubdued. So that Chriſt may have an abſolute Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over your whole Man, Body and Soul, and that you may be happy in his Government.</p>
            <p>And as for God's <hi>Kingdom of Glory,</hi> or the Glorious Manifeſtation of Chriſt's coming to diſpenſe a final Pardon to his Faithful Subjects, and to admit them to the Participation of his Joy and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: and to pronounce a direful Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon his obſtinate Enemies; ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to be Tormented with the Devil and his Angels; even for the Coming of this Kingdom you are alſo to pray, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Holy ones under the Altar, <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>A farther Account of the Things to be Pray'd for.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AND having Pray'd God thus to rule in your heart by Grace, that you may be fit for his coming in Glory to Crown his Servants, and Torment his
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:41876:66"/>Enemies; you are to Pray again that God would enable you to do both his ſecret and revealed Will, and that you may patiently and contentedly ſubmit to the former; and readily and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully perform the latter, as far as it is ſet down in his Holy Word. Now Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God's Law and Submiſſion to his Providence, are both requir'd to the doing of his Will. For you are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to obſerve what he enjoyns or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits, but alſo to ſubmit to whatever happens to you according to his Good Will and Pleaſure, whether it be Miſery or Happineſs. And he who taught you to do thus did illuſtrate it with his own Example, when with an admirable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation he Pray'd, <hi>Not mine, O Father, but thy Will be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the manner of your <hi>Doing God's Will,</hi> is taken from the Pattern of the Holy Angels, who are God's miniſtring Spirits, executing his Commandments with readineſs, fidelity and perſeverance; flying upon his errand with the wings of Love and Zeal. But ſeeing you find (perhaps) in your ſelf a reluctancy to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:41876:67"/>do thus, and that your Duty herein is often delay'd through Idleneſs, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted through Vanity, ſo that your Obedience moves heavily and is clogg'd with fears, and broken off by tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; you are to ſupplicate the Father of all Mercies, that he would beſtow upon you that Zeal and Affection for his Service, wherewith the Holy Angels are Inſpired: to the intent that you may as they, do his Will with Fervency and Chearfulneſs. And that following the Examples of their Obedience, whilſt you are on Earth, you may be joyn'd with them, and your bleſſed Brethren in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to ſing eternal Praiſes in Heaven.</p>
            <p>And as our Lord in the three firſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions of his Prayer compris'd all things reſpecting God and his Glory, for which you are to Pray: So in the next three Petitions he has ſum'd up whatſoever you have need to deſire, reſpecting your own or your Neighbours Wants and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities. And you may obſerve that the things relating to God's Glory, are by our Saviour's Preſcription firſt to be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited, and if this be rightly done, you can
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:41876:67"/>ſcarce miſs of the reſt. For all other things ſhall be given to them, <hi>Who firſt ſeek the Kingdom of God and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; Matth.</hi> 6.33. And ſeeing God's Glory is of greater moment than yours or any man's Wants, therefore you are to Pray for the firſt. And yet ſeeing you are neither all <hi>Fleſh,</hi> nor all <hi>Spirit,</hi> but a compound of both, and that both have Needs to be ſupplyed, you are to Pray for the relief of both.</p>
            <p>And firſt you are to beg a ſupply for your Bodily Neceſſities, all which our Lord comprehended under the name of Bread. Which <hi>Word</hi> ſignifies outward comforts. And in Praying God to give you this, you declare your ſole depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to be on him for this preſent life, and for all things that ſupport it. And the begging them of God, declares like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe your abhorrence of all unjuſt and indirect ways to obtain them.</p>
            <p>Next, by the adjunct <hi>(Daily)</hi> added to Bread, you evidence your contented<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with preſent neceſſaries, and your purpoſe to Pray continually for them. Which likewiſe declares your truſt in
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:41876:68"/>God; and that you caſt your Cares up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; acknowledging that all you have or expect, are from his bounteous Hand, and ſanctified by his Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>And this Petition for <hi>Daily Bread</hi> was no doubt taken from that Prayer of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which was thus; <q rend="inline">The neceſſities of thy People <hi>Iſrael</hi> are many, and their knowledge ſmall (ſo that they know not how to diſcloſe their Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities) let it be thy good Pleaſure to give to every man what ſufficeth for food, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And the Petition for <hi>Daily Bread</hi> is by ſome thus paraphras'd, <q rend="inline">Provide for us to morrows Bread, and give it us to day, that we be not ſolicitous for to morrow: for ſufficient unto the day is the evil thereof.</q>
            </p>
            <p>All things needful for this preſent life come from God, and the Petition for <hi>Daily Bread,</hi> ſhews that you are not to deſire them all at once, but that he would diſtribute them by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, according as you need them. That by this means you may never be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of, nor deſiſt in Praying for them.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:41876:68"/>For if you ſhould poſſeſs them in too great abundance, and as it were in a heap, you might be in danger to reſt contented within your ſelf, and forget to call upon the Lord; <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.8, 9. Chriſt in this Petition for <hi>(Daily Bread)</hi> ſeems to have reflected upon the ſending of the <hi>Manna</hi> and as that was daily gather'd, ſo this might be daily begg'd and given.</p>
            <p>Some of the Fathers have Allegoriz'd this Petition, and underſtood it of <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> and the partaking of him in the <hi>Bleſſed Euchariſt:</hi> which does nouriſh the Soul unto Life Eternal, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Bread does the temporal Life of the Body. And tho' I could wiſh that in this ſenſe the Requeſt for <hi>(Daily Bread)</hi> were both underſtood and practis'd, and that now, as in the Primitive Times the Sacrament of Chriſt's Death were daily celebrated; yet I think the Petition is beſt interpreted, of all manner of Food, that is neceſſary for the preſervation of human Life, and of whatever is requir'd to ſupport Man's frail Nature; which could not be particularly expreſs'd in ſo ſhort a Form.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:41876:69"/>
            <p>But if you look not farther than to your Bodily needs, even to that of your Soul, the ſupply of the firſt may prove a Miſery and not a Happineſs, if the other be neglected. Now the firſt thing you are to beg for your Soul is the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of your Sins, and that God would not exact their penalty, but that for the ſake of the ſatisfaction Chriſt made to his Divine Juſtice, he would mercifully acquit you from their Guilt and Puniſhment.</p>
            <p>And to the end that you may not forfeit God's Pardon to you, by Deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yours to your Brethren, you are humbly to beſeech the Almighty to give you thoſe bowels of Compaſſion towards others, when they treſpaſs againſt you; which you ſtand in need of when you treſpaſs againſt them; and if you who, through the corruption of Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are prone to revenge, can through God's Grace forgive others, you need not doubt but your Heavenly Father, whoſe Goodneſs is infinite, will forgive you; For it is certainly true: That if you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give Men, you ſhall be forgiven of God.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:41876:69"/>Not that you are to give Law to God, or to ground your Prayers on the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of your own Works; but that you ſubſcribe to God's order to Pardon, if you purpoſe to be Pardon'd. And here take notice, that (according to <hi>Diodati</hi>) the Forgiveneſs of Treſpaſſes, for which you Pray, cannot be underſtood of the general remiſſion of Sins, in reſpect of the everlaſting Judgment; which has no other cauſe or ground before God, but Chriſt's ſatisfaction and interceſſion, but of the pardon of particular faults of Believers, in regard of puniſhments in this life. It was a rule of the Wiſe Men among the <hi>Jews,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">That our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning of thoſe who have injur'd us, is rewarded by God with hearing our Prayers for Forgiveneſs.</q> And to this purpoſe are the words of <hi>Siracides, Ecclus</hi> 28.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">He that revengeth ſhall find vengeance from the Lord, and he will ſurely keep his ſins in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. Forgive thy Neighbour the hurt he hath done unto thee ſo ſhall thy Sins alſo be forgiven when thou prayeſt. One man beareth hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:41876:70"/>another, and doth he ſeek par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don from the Lord? He ſheweth no mercy to a man which is like himſelf: and doth he ask forgiveneſs of his own Sins? If he that is but Fleſh and Blood nouriſh hatred, who will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat for pardon of his Sins?</q>
            </p>
            <p>But you are not to conclude from hence that Pardon from God depends only on your pardoning of others, or that it is merited by it, but that it is moſt reaſonable, that you who requeſt forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your Offences againſt God, ſhould forgive the Offences of your Brethren; whoſe Offences are leſs in number and value, and not committed perhaps with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your provocation. Take heed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leſt by your Malice and want of Charity to others, you bring not God's wrath and indignation on your ſelf.</p>
            <p>Deliverance from the power of Sin, and all temptations to commit it, is the next thing reſpecting your Soul, that you are to ſeek for, at the hands of your Creator. Now, of your ſelf you are unable to withſtand thoſe multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of temptations which daily aſſault
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:41876:70"/>you; ſo that you have need continually to have recourſe to the Divine aſſiſtance, and to implore God either wholly to remove all temptations, or ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain their power and malice, that they do not overcome you. The former is not to be hop'd, and ſo not to be pray'd for. For the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, will never give over ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, alluring, and tempting you to Sin. Satan (as his name ſignifies) is to the Tempter, who being miſerable by Sin, labours to make all like himſelf: And that he ſpares none, was ſeen in his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to ſet upon our Saviour; whom he would have tempted to the moſt horrid iniquity, the worſhip of himſelf. And as this ſhews that none can eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape his temptations, ſo it likewiſe ſhews that it is no Sin to be tempted, but that all the fault lies in yielding to the temptation: and this ariſes from (that great Impoſtor) your own Heart, which is deceitful above all things, and deſperately wicked.</p>
            <p>It ought then to be your earneſt and inceſſant ſupplication to him, who can
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:41876:71"/>reſtrain the powers of darkneſs, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuate the miſchievous devices of Hell and all its Agents, that he would keep you from all evil circumſtances, and dangerous occaſions leading to Sin: that he would ſuppreſs in you all inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to evil, and not leave you to your ſelf, nor to be tempted, and <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away of your own luſts, and enticed:</hi> That he would not unchain, and let looſe, the infernal foes to aſſail and over-maſter you by their accurſed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements; but that <hi>you may reſiſt unto Blood, and be crown'd with conqueſt over them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if your Heavenly Father for great purpoſes leads you into any ſignal tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als and temptations, then do you reſign your ſelf to his abſolute pleaſure; hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeeching his <hi>paternal tenderneſs,</hi> to limit and controul the Tempter, and to reſtrain your conſent. And tho' it ought to be your great grief to be at any time enticed to offend God, yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be any great diſcomfort, ſo long as God is pleas'd to relieve you from doing the evil to which you are tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:41876:71"/>and <hi>together with the temptation, to make you a way to eſcape.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> have a Form, which they call the ſhort Prayer, which is an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome or Abridgment of their longer Prayers; and it was a rule among them, <q rend="inline">That he who had a promptneſs in Prayer, was to pray the eighteen Prayers, but he who wanted this promptneſs, was to uſe the ſhort Prayer, which was a Recollection out of the other, and is as follows:</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>OUR Father which art in Heaven, be gracious unto us. O Lord our God hallowed be thy Name, and let the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thee be Glorified in Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and upon earth here below. Let thy Kingdom reign over us now and for ever, Remit and forgive unto all whatſoever they have done againſt us. And lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil thing. For thine is the Kingdom and thou ſhalt reign in Glory (or Power) for ever and ever,</hi>
               </q> vid. Mr. John Gregory, Pag. 168.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:41876:72"/>
            <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>Prayer to be made in the plural number.</hi> Amen.</head>
            <p>AND both this Summary, and the larger Prayer, were uſed by the <hi>Jews</hi> in the daies of our Saviour: who out of them collected the Form, which he taught his Diſciples, and which is now uſed by all Chriſtians. But when our Lord gave this Prayer, he did not null or make void the other Prayers uſed by the <hi>Jews,</hi> nor did he intend that his <hi>Followers</hi> ſhould uſe <hi>his Prayer</hi> and none other: but he gave it as an abſolute, perfect Form by which our imperfect Prayers are to be regulated, and to be an abſtract of all we are to Pray for. So that if any thing be wanting in our Prayers, it is to be ſupplied by adding unto them <hi>the Lord's Prayer.</hi> Which Chriſt (I ſay) gave not to extinguiſh but to regulate our Prayers; and to be added unto them, and to render them
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:41876:72"/>perfect and conſummate. For it contains the heads of all things that you can either want or deſire to have.</p>
            <p>And our Lord in his Heavenly Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſo order'd the compoſure of his Prayer, that it might differ as little as poſſible from the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Form, and that it might likewiſe be fit to be ſaid by all. And I think there is none (of what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſoever) who own God to be the Father, or Maker of Heaven and Earth, who may not pertinently make uſe of the Lords Prayer, and deſire every thing that therein is ſet down.</p>
            <p>It is obſervable, that the <hi>Jews</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all their Prayers to be ſaid in the Plural Number, tho' he that ſaid them was alone by himſelf, and they did it for this reaſon, <q rend="inline">That it might never ſeem as tho' a man were cut off from the congregation.</q> And they have this commendable Canon, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">He that prays ought always when he prays, to joyn with the Church.</q> Which Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non they do not ſtrictly underſtand only of Prayers ſaid in the Synagogue, but whereſoever they are made in the world.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:41876:73"/>And when a <hi>Jew</hi> is moſt alone he is to ſay Prayers in the <hi>plural</hi> and not in the <hi>ſingular</hi> number. In which number our Saviour alſo has taught us to pray. So that when you are in the greateſt ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and ſeparation from company you are to own your union with the Church, and Communion with all true Believers, for whoſe happineſs you ought to pray as well as for your own.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church Ordain'd that all their Publick Prayers ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with <hi>(Amen.)</hi> I ſay Publick Prayers, for, in their Private or <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacterical</hi> Prayers it was omitted. And it was a ſign thoſe Prayers were Publick to which <hi>Amen</hi> was added, and a ſign they were otherwiſe when it was not uſed. And the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church retains the ſame Cuſtom, adding <hi>Amen</hi> to all her Prayers. Which is a word of that weight and moment, that it ought never to be omitted. For by ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> you declare your truſt and aſſurance that God will grant the things you ask ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Will. It being one ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial branch of your confidence in God;
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:41876:73"/>that if <hi>you ask any thing according to his Will,</hi> and not your own fancy, <hi>he heareth you.</hi> By ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> to the Publick Prayers you expreſs your approbation of them, that you agree with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and preſent but one common vote unto God. And when there is a happy harmony and conſent of heart and voice in praying for things lawful and expedient, you may be aſſured that he who has promis'd to grant the Requeſts of two or three gather'd together in his Name, will much more incline his ear to a pious multitude, to a numerous Congregation, met ſolemnly to beg his Bleſſings.</p>
            <p>But beſides all this your humble, hearty, and zealous ſaying <hi>Amen,</hi> ſhews your attentiveneſs to the Publick Prayers, and that you are neither aſleep nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advertent when they are made.</p>
            <p>And indeed one way to quicken your attention, is to conſider that you are to ſay an hearty <hi>Amen</hi> to every Prayer, and as it were to ſet your ſeal unto it by ſo doing. And by ſaying <hi>Amen,</hi> you alſo let the Hearer of Prayers know that
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:41876:74"/>you hope and believe to have your ſhare in the good things that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd: and that on the contrary you do not expect any benefit by the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which you do not ſign and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm by your <hi>Amen.</hi> In which ſingle word all your own Wants are ſum'd up, and theirs alſo for whom you pray. And we read that the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians thought the ſaying an hearty <hi>Amen</hi> to be of ſo great importance, that they pronounc'd it with a ſort of voci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feration and affectionate earneſtneſs; which is enough to ſhame and awaken their negligence, who either regard not at all to ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> or do it with ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking a drowſineſs and indifferency, as if it were all one to them whether God would grant or deny their Requeſt; whether he did hearken to their Prayers, or ſtop his ears againſt them: which being conſider'd, will (I hope) have the happy influence to make you ſo at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive to Prayer, as to cloſe it with ſuch a ſenſible <hi>Amen, as that the Lord God may ſay ſo too;</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.36.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:41876:74"/>
            <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>Of our Lord's Doxology.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AND having now given you this plain familiar account of the Things you are to deſire of God, as they are ſet down in the <hi>Divine Summary</hi> left us by our Lord; give me leave for (a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion) to preſent you with a ſhort ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the drift and deſign, of the ſcope and end of Prayer; which is none other than God's Glory, and your own Benefit.</p>
            <p>That God's Glory ought to be the firſt and principal end and drift of Prayer, is naturally to be concluded from the Doxology, wherewith both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have ever cloſed their Supplications. That Doxology was us'd by the <hi>Hebrews</hi> in <hi>David</hi>'s time, is plain from his own practice; who praiſed the Lord before all the People, and ſaid, <q rend="inline">Bleſſed be thou, Lord God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> our Father, for ever and ever. Thine
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:41876:75"/>O Lord, is the Greatneſs, and the Power, and the Glory, and the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the Majeſty, for all that is in the Heaven and in the Earth, is thine; thine is the Kingdom, O Lord, and thou art exalted as Head above all. Both Riches and Honour come from thee, and thou Reigneſt over all, and in thy Hand is Power and Might, and in thine Hand it is to make Great, and to give Strength unto all. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our God, we thank thee, and praiſe thy glorious Name. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29, 10, 11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And we find a Doxology added to all the Publick Prayers of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which was follow'd by our Saviour in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Form. And tho' ſome both in the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Church, have look'd upon the Doxology at the end of the Lord's Prayer, <q rend="inline">to be a Spurious Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition put in by ſome well-meaning man, who did not well know what he did; yet I ſee no ground for this ſaying.</q> For ſince it is granted by all, That our Saviour took every Petition of his Prayer out of the <hi>Jewiſh Eucho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues,</hi> it may juſtly be thought that he
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:41876:75"/>thence alſo took the Doxology, and added it to his Prayer, as the <hi>Jews</hi> to theirs.</p>
            <p>Now, the Doxology is not only a Form of Praiſe and Thanksgiving, fit and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to be the cloſing up of all Devotions, in token that they are directed to God's Honor, but it alſo contains the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal grounds of making your Addreſſes unto God. For in ſaying, <hi>Thine is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the Power, and the Glory, for ever and ever:</hi> You acknowledg all thoſe excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to be in God, which are the true and chief motives of Prayer, and which give life and ſpirit to that Heavenly Duty, and to all the Graces therein to be exercis'd.</p>
            <p>And firſt, your Faith is greatly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in the expectation of the good things you pray for, when you ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely revolve that you beg them of him, who is the only univerſal, abſolute, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Lord and Sovereign of the World. And that he is eaſily intreated of his Subjects, and takes pleaſure in their Protection and Happineſs. Only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that at the ſame time you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God's Kingdom, you own your ſelf to be his Subject, and that it
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:41876:76"/>is your duty to obey his Laws, and to ſubmit intirely to his Government, and not to countenance any one rebel Luſt againſt him.</p>
            <p>And when (Secondly) you aſcribe Power unto God, you profeſs your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of his All-ſufficiency, and that you preſent your Petition to one, who is able and willing to grant it. For if he wanted either Will or Power to give what you beg, it were enough utterly to diſcourage your Application. But ſeeing that God has <hi>the bowels of a Father, and the arm of a King, and a</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign right to diſpoſe of every thing as he pleaſes, he is in all reſpects fitly qualified to grant the requeſt you make unto him. And although your own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs might juſtly hinder you from receiving any favour at his hand, yet he will not withhold what you rightly ſue for: That his free Grace may have that Glory from you which he hath from all to whom he has been formerly bountiful.</p>
            <p>There is an excellent Honour ariſing unto God from his own <hi>infinite perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and the effects thereof; and he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:41876:76"/>it ſhould be paid him by all his Creatures both in Heaven and Earth. And tho' all ſolemn Acts of Religion ſhould aim at his honour, and be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to it, as their genuine end; yet in a more eminent manner this honour is deſign'd him in Prayer. For were it otherwiſe, Our Lord would not have begun his Prayer with, <hi>Hallowed be thy Name,</hi> nor have concluded it with, <hi>Thine is the Kingdom, the Power, and the Glory.</hi> And if the glory of what you have, and are, be not aſcrib'd to that Omnipotent Being from whom you receive them; <hi>If you ſacrifice unto your Net, and burn incenſe unto your Drag;</hi> if you attribute any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition or endowment to your ſelf, you rob God of his Honour (of which he is moſt tender) and can be truly ſaid neither to Hallow Gods Name, nor to give him Glory.</p>
            <p>And here it will be natural for you to conſider that the Kingdom, Power, and Glory of God, are not fading and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory, but permanent, eternal, and for ever and ever. For if it were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and that you were to make your Prayers to a mortal, mutable God, one
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:41876:77"/>ſubject to change of mind and death, it would leſſen the vigor of your Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But ſeeing the object thereof is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever: and that his Kingdom, Power, and Glory, are from everlaſting to everlaſting; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God is a merciful Father and ſtill ready to hear the cry of his Penitent Children; and ſeeing he is for ever a King, loving and helpful to his Subjects; and for ever one, for whoſe Glory it is to grant your Addreſſes; theſe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations give you ſpirit to call upon him with comfort and aſſurance, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent your doubting of his gracious Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience for the things you crave of him for the ſake of his Kingdom, Power and Glory.</p>
            <p>All communications of Goodneſs flow from God, and it is but juſt that they ſhould return to him again in Sacrifices of Praiſe and Adoration. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let it be your care to aſcribe unto him the honour of all you have, and do. For this will keep you from that oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and vain-glory, to which man's proud nature is not a little inclinable, eſpecially in matters of Religion, which
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:41876:77"/>being obſerv'd by our Saviour, he ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caution'd all men againſt it, bidding them by all means to avoid Vanity and Pride in the duties of Religion; and particularly in Alms, and Prayers. In Alms he requires ſuch a Secrecy, as that if the left hand had eyes and ears, yet it ſhould neither ſee nor hear what the right hand did, that by this means the Alms-giver might utterly be freed from all ſuſpicion of Vain-glory.</p>
            <p>The Scribes indeed gave their Alms with ſound of trumpet, they call'd the Poor together from every quarter, not that they ſhould all partake of their Alms, but to have the more Spectators. All they aim'd at was the empty rumour and vogue of being Bountiful. For which they were ſo far from deſerving any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from God, that they deſerv'd a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, for their Folly, Diſſimulation, and Injuſtice. For their Folly, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring Humane things to Divine; for their Diſſimulation, in impoſing upon the world, by their counterfeit Piety; and for their Injuſtice, in aſſuming that Praiſe to themſelves which was due only unto God.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:41876:78"/>
            <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>The End and Drift of Prayer,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>AND as our Lord caution'd all men againſt Vain-glory in giving Alms, ſo he likewiſe caution'd them againſt the ſame in Prayer. In which he would have all carefully to eſchew the faſhion and mode of Hypocrites, Perſonators and Actors in Religion, who (among the <hi>Jews</hi>) were wont to pray ſtanding in the Synagogues, and corners of the ſtreets, places of publick concourſe, where they were ſure to have many to ſee them. But, inſtead of affecting any ſuch po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularity, he would have you ſtudiouſly to avoid it, by going in your cloſet, and ſhutting the doors, and with all poſſible privacy <hi>to pray to your Father which is in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and your Father which ſeeth in ſecret ſhall reward you openly.</hi> Not that our Lord condemns Publick Prayer, which the Church has practis'd ever ſince ſhe had a being upon Earth, but rather than that you ſhould be thought to pray for
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:41876:78"/>Oſtentation, he would have you retire from all worldly company, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did when he wreſtled with the Angel, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.24. And in your private Prayers (of which Chriſt Jeſus ſpeaks S. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.) to be as private as you can; to go into the moſt ſecret Apartment, and there unboſom your ſelf to God. For tho' he himſelf be inviſible, yet he ſees you, how ſecret ſoever you are, and all that you do in ſecret. And he that is thus the beholder of Private Devotions ſhall reward you before men and Angels. Be content therefore that God looks upon and eſteems you, that he is a witneſs of what you do, ſeeing it is from him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone that you expect your reward. But if in a duty wherein God's Glory is ſo nearly concern'd, you take in ſo poor an acceſſion as the praiſe of men, it is but juſt that that ſhould be your reward, and that you receive none other from God; to whom nothing can be more diſpleaſing than to ſee Oſtentation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe in your Devotion, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you ſeek the applauſe of men more than his Glory. Whereas in all your worſhip of God, private or publick, your
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:41876:79"/>eye ſhould be ſtill on his Honour, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding nothing ſo much as to have him approve your doings, becauſe he only is able to reward them.</p>
            <p>And tho God's Glory is to be the firſt and principal end of your Prayers, yet in ſubordination to this, you may alſo deſign your own benefit, and that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For theſe are very conſiſtent and need not be ſeparate. For at the ſame time that you uſe Prayer as an Act of Worſhip ſolely due unto God, you may alſo uſe it as a means appointed by him to obtain his Bleſſings; which are either Spiritual or Secular, belonging to your Soul, or Body. The firſt are Grace, Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Pardon of Sins; in praying for which you may be peremtory and abſolute. But in praying for temporal Bleſſings, you are to be conditional, and to uſe reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſubmiſſion, and in craving them never to deſign any thing that is mean and ſordid.</p>
            <p>And (1.) if you deſire, and God gives you, Secular Power and Authority, do not abuſe or proſtitute it to wicked, unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purpoſes, ſuch as the gratifying of your ſpleen, and revenge, and the oppreſſion of
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:41876:79"/>thoſe you hate. But imploy your Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity <hi>in undoing the heavy burthens; in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting the impetent, and him that has no helper: in breaking the jaws of the wicked, and plucking the Spoil out of their teeth; in delivering the poor that cry, and the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and him that has none to help:</hi> In ſhort, uſe the authority God gives you, in <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Juſtice, and maintaining Truth,</hi> in being a Terror to evil doers, and a Praiſe and encouragement to them that do well.</p>
            <p>And for worldly Riches, do not deſire them for ſuch low regards as the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of Pride, Pomp, Luxury, or the like; but that you may have wherewith to maintain good Works, and to be in your proſperity (what <hi>Job</hi> was in his) <hi>Eyes to the blind, and feet to the lame. That the bleſſing of him who is ready to periſh may come upon you, and that by your means the heart of the needy may ſing for joy, Job.</hi> 29.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Let your Prayers and Endeavours go hand in hand; for the former without the latter is trifling and mockery; and the latter without the former, vanity and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption: you can never rightly deſire what you do not by all good means la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to obtain. To pray for that which
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:41876:80"/>you do not endeavour after, is to be the moral of the Clown in the Apologue, who call'd to <hi>Hercules</hi> to help him out with his mir'd Cart, without ſetting his own ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the wheel; The eye to Heaven, and the hand to the Helm, is the old rule; Supplications and Endeavours are never to be disjoyn'd, no good is to be expected from either of them when alone.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Obſerve what anſwer God makes, and what returns you receive to your Prayers: And in particular conſider that his gracious Providence may often deny you ſome temporal Bleſſings as ſeeing them leſs fit for you to receive. But then he gives you others in their ſtead, which his infinite Goodneſs and Wiſdom ſees are more for your advantage. And tho' God has promis'd to give to them that ask, yet it is with theſe limitations, <hi>viz.</hi> That he ſees it good for you: and that he has not by ſome particular Decree determin'd the contrary. As for example, If God has determin'd to deſtroy an impenitent Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is not all the Prayers of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt men on Earth, can prevail with God to preſerve it. And of this you have a dreadful inſtance in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 14. where it
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:41876:80"/>is evident that when God has reſolv'd to puniſh a Land with any kind of Scourge, he will not forbear to do it for any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of interceſſion.</p>
            <p>Finally, whether God grants or denies your requeſts, it is your duty to reſign your will to his, and to affect your mind with a profound ſenſe of his infinit good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in that, without difficulty of Acceſs, he admits you to pray unto him, and that you need not doubt of acceptance, if you pray as you ought. And to ſhew how you are to do this, has been my care in what I now preſent you. God proſper what has been ſaid, and make it to be for his own Glory, and your eternal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, through Jeſus Chriſt. To whom with God the Father and God the Holy Ghoſt, be Praiſe, Glory, Adoration, and Thankſgiving, for ever and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:41876:81"/>
            <head>Books Written by the Reverend <hi>L.A.</hi> D. D. <hi>Dean</hi> of <hi>Lichfield.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WEſt Barbary, <hi>or an Account of the Cuſtoms and Revolutions of that Countrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Preſent State of the</hi> Jews <hi>in</hi> Barbary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Firſt State of</hi> Mahomediſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Primitive Inſtitution, <hi>or a Diſcourſe of</hi> Catechiſing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Modeſt Plea <hi>for the</hi> Clergy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An</hi> Introduction <hi>of the</hi> Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Catechumen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Account of the</hi> Millennium.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Genuine uſe of the two</hi> Sacraments, <hi>viz.</hi> Baptiſm, <hi>and the</hi> Lord's Supper, <hi>with the</hi> Chriſtians Obligation <hi>frequently to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Latter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Hiſtory <hi>of the</hi> Hereſie <hi>denying the</hi> Divinity <hi>of</hi> Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Chriſtians <hi>daily</hi> Sacrifice <hi>duly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, being a practical Diſcourſe of the right Performance of</hi> Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Account of</hi> Tangier <hi>during the Earl of</hi> Tiviot<hi>'s Government: in a Letter to a Perſon of Quality.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41876:81"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
